<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some stop to the gangrene of Arminianism lately promoted by M. John Goodwin in his book entituled, Redemption redeemed, or, The doctrine of election &amp; reprobation : in six sermons, opened and cleared from the old Pelagian and late Arminian errors / by Richard Resburie ...</title>
            <author>Resbury, Richard, 1607-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 224 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57067</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16922</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12280573</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12280573</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58707</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57067)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58707)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 192:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some stop to the gangrene of Arminianism lately promoted by M. John Goodwin in his book entituled, Redemption redeemed, or, The doctrine of election &amp; reprobation : in six sermons, opened and cleared from the old Pelagian and late Arminian errors / by Richard Resburie ...</title>
                  <author>Resbury, Richard, 1607-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 128, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Wright ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collction, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665. --  Redemption redeemed.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
               <term>Arminianism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58707:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58707:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Some ſtop to the GANGRENE OF ARMINIANISM, Lately promoted by M. <hi>John Goodwin'</hi> in his Book entituled, Redemption Redeemed. <hi>OR,</hi> The Doctrine of Election &amp; Reprobation IN SIX SERMONS Opened and cleared from the old Pelagian and late Arminian Errors.</p>
            <p>By RICHARD RESBURIE, Miniſter of the Goſpell in Oundle in Northamptonſhire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Wright</hi> at the Kings-Head in the OLD-BAYLY. 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58707:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58707:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou haſt here a ſmall piece preſented to thy view, which hath above theſe three years laine concealed with the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, as thou mayeſt perceive by the <hi>Imprimatur;</hi> neither had it yet looked abroad, had not thoſe main Truths of God in it aſſerted concerning his Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting and Redeeming Grace, whereon eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the throne of his glory is raiſed, wherein is the peculiar treaſure of his Saints, been of late by the daring hand of that unhappy man M. <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> in his wretched Treatiſe by him called, (but miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called) <hi>Redemption Redeemed,</hi> been ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſaulted. In the firſt place my hearty Prayer is, <hi>The Lord rebuke him;</hi> and if that peculiar grace which for the preſent he ſo
<pb facs="tcp:58707:3"/>ſeriouſly deſpiſeth, and ſo boldly bids defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to, ſhall yet magnifie it ſelfe in ſaving him, though by fire, yet let the zeal of the Lord for his own moſt precious truth burn his worke, for it is ſtubble: Nay, when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that grace ſhall viſit him indeed, with the diſcovery of the truth, as it is in Jeſus, his own hands will be forward to pul down what he hath built. In the ſecond place my hopes are, and indeed my confident expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, that the Spirit of the Lord ſhall ſend forth ſome faithfull aſſertors of his Truth, not only to encounter him, but to confound his Doctrine, and for the good of his Elect ones in this Nation, ſuch of them as through weakneſs of judgement, and unskilfulneſs in the myſterie of Chriſt, are liable to be ſeduced by ſuch a Spirit of Errour, (onely the foundation of God ſtands ſure,) to ſtrike his weapons out of his hand, as they have been already ſtruck out of the hands or his great Maſters <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius</hi> and <hi>Corvinus,</hi> and the reſt of that miſchievous faculty: Neither hath he, for ought I can (and without partiality) diſcerne, at all repaired their loſſe, onely concealing it from vulgar eyes, he treads with confidence in their beaten ſteps, and that nothing may want to ſet it off brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, challengeth an whole Univerſity to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move
<pb facs="tcp:58707:3"/>him. (Doubtleſſe ſuch modeſty and ingenuity, muſt needs be the character of the Spirit of Truth in him:) In the meane time till a further Antidote ſhall be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by a more skilfull hand, I have adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured to adminiſter this which lay by me, if the Lord may pleaſe to bleſſe it for ſome checke to that ſpreading poiſon. And this let me ſay, though it be no Anſwer directed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to his Booke, for it was compoſed long before his diſcourſe ſaw the light, yet doth it mainly inſiſt upon the foundation of all, <hi>viz.</hi> the Decrees of God, endeavouring to cleare according to the Scripture, (the onely key of this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,) the Doctrine of Election and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, which being once well ſetled, his errors about the following Doctrines, that of Redemption, the perſeverance of the Saints, &amp;c. are ſmitten at the root; withall in the proſecution of thoſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Decrees, the other Doctrines con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted fall in to be diſcourſed; neither have I declined the maine Objections which by the Arminian Family are wont to be made about theſe Doctrines; ſo that the ſubſtance of the whole Controverſie is therein handled: But the beſt account I can give hereof, is briefly to ſet down the order of the Treatiſe, which is as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58707:4"/>
In the firſt and ſecond Sermon is hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Doctrine of Election and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation joyntly, and this in opening the ninth Chapter to the <hi>Romans,</hi> from Verſ. 1. to 24. wherein the <hi>Abſolute Decree</hi> is maintained. In the third Sermon the Doctrine of Election apart, and therein <hi>Abſolute Election further aſſerted.</hi> In the fourth Sermon the Doctrine of Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation apart, and therein <hi>Abſolute Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation proved.</hi> In the fifth Sermon thoſe Texts of Scripture cleared which are wont mainely to be objected againſt the Doctrines in this Diſcourſe maintained, and therein the Arminian Doctrines, 1. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the antecedent and conſequent Will: 2. About the improvement of naturalls, for the obtainment of ſpiritualls, exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. In the ſixth and laſt Sermon three other Objections are anſwered; 1. That which chargeth the former Doctrine as <hi>making God the Author of ſinne.</hi> 2. That which chargeth the ſame Doctrine as <hi>ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring God cruell,</hi> or at leaſt not ſo merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as the Scripture repreſents him. 3. That which chargeth it <hi>with deſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling man of the liberty of his Will,</hi> and indeed here is the <hi>Diana.</hi> In theſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections are the knots; I have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſingled them out, not that I have
<pb facs="tcp:58707:4"/>ſuch an overweening opinion of my ſelfe, as to thinke my ſelfe amongſt the ableſt to unite them, but indeed very farre below many of my brethren. But, 1. It is not faire dealing with a Controverſie to paſſe by the main Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections: 2. I hope what is here ſaid in anſwer to them may not be without fruit, for the further eſtabliſhment of ſome in the Truth. 3. I was willing hereby to give occaſion to ſome one or other Scribe in this our Iſrael more throughly inſtructed unto the Kingdome of Heaven, to bring out of his treaſure things new and old, for ſetting theſe precious Truths of God more faire in the eyes of his people: And here I now thanke Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> whoſe darkneſſe, I doubt not, will occaſion more light, his boldneſſe (confident I am) will excite modeſty; I will not ſay, what an edge his ſometimes imperiall dictates, inſtead of Arguments, (as is the Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian mode) ſometimes his monſtrous Concluſions, ſometimes his wreſted Quotations, ſometimes his uncouth Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, ſometimes his conſequentiall Blaſphemy, will put upon the ſpirits of ſome whom the Lord ſhall honour to
<pb facs="tcp:58707:5"/>reſcue his Truth out of his hands, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I am perſwaded the zeale of the Lord will doe it: Which, and a fruitfull bleſſing thereupon, ſhall be the earneſt Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(Reader) </salute> 
               <signed>Thy Servant in and for the Truth,
<hi>Richard Resbury.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58707:5"/>
            <head>THE FIRST SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 11 Chap. verſe 7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But the Election hath obtained it, and the reſt were blinded, or hardened.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle is here taking up againe the ſame diſcourſe which in the ninth Chapter he had begun, and hitherto continued; now win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding up all towards a concluſion.</p>
            <p>For our more diſtinct underſtanding of it, we muſt firſt obſerve the occaſion, then the diſcourſe it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The occaſion; an objection which might ariſe from the Jews refuſall of the Goſpell, which the Apoſtle doth ſo prevent and anſwer, as in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer he doth clearly open the great myſtery of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Predeſtination.</p>
            <p>The Objection ariſeth thus; The Apoſtle having formerly preached the truth of the Goſpell, in that maine Article of juſtification by faith alone without the works of the Law: Hence this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; if that be truth, and the onely of life; how comes it to paſſe that the Jews Gods cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted <hi>Iſrael</hi> generally refuſe it? ſticking to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58707:6"/>Law for righteouſneſſe to life: Hence it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that God hath made void his Covenant ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon <hi>Abraham</hi> for himſelfe, and his ſeed, in that he hath now caſt off his people; the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> this in the firſt verſe <hi>(I ſay then hath God caſt away his people?)</hi> But then they aſſume, but God hath not made void his Covenant; therefore they conclude againſt the truth of the Goſpell, that juſtification is not by faith, as the Apoſtle taught.</p>
            <p>For anſwer; The Apoſtle retaining the truth of the Goſpell; firſt diſclaimes, then refutes the objection.</p>
            <p>Firſt he diſclaimes it, <hi>(God forbid)</hi> God makes good his Covenant to the utmoſt. Secondly, He refutes it. 1. By ſpeciall inſtance of himſelfe, <hi>For I alſo am an Iſraelite &amp;c.</hi> verſ. 1. this concludes God hath not caſt away all his people; but what if ſome? Therefore in the ſecond place, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers by diſtinction, vindicating the faithfulneſs of God, that not one of his Covenanted ones hath he caſt away: the ſumme of his anſwer here is this; of the people of God, ſo by outward call, and within the outward adminiſtration of the Covenant; ſome he foreknew, others he did not foreknow; theſe whom he foreknew, are his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple indeed, to whom not onely the outward ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, but the ſpirituall and eternall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of the Covenant do belong; theſe he hath not caſt off, the reſt he hath; yet herein his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe not lyable to exception, for as much as they never were truly his Covenanted ones, onely pretenders to, and ſeemingly in the Covenant. This is the ſummary meaning of thoſe words, verſ. 2. <hi>God hath not caſt away his people which he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58707:6"/>foreknew:</hi> (By the way obſerve, if any of Gods covenanted ones ſhould fall ſhort of eternall life, making defection from the truth; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle leaves God under that guilt which the objection here chargeth him with <hi>(viz)</hi> that he breaks Covenant, and caſts away his people con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the undertaking of his Covenant;) but this by the way againſt that horrid Tenent of the Saints finall apoſtacy.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle having thus anſwered by diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he goes on; firſt confirming, then concluding his anſwer; in the concluſion likewiſe explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what he meant by this fore-knowledge of God concerning his people.</p>
            <p>For confirmation that God hath not caſt off his people whome he foreknew, he inſtanceth the Churches ſtate in <hi>Elijah's</hi> time, from the 2d. to the 5th. verſ. The ſum is this, though the whole Nation in generall fell off from God to abomin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Idols, and no where true worſhippers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, yet then had God his reſerved number, cleaving to the truth, and obtaining life. The concluſion is verſ. the 5th. by application of the former inſtance; the ſum this: though at this preſent time the Nation of the Jews generally oppoſe the Goſpell, and bring damnation upon themſelves; yet there is a remnant according to the Election of grace who embrace the Goſpell, and find life; where together with the concluſion, we have his interpretation, the people whom God fore-knew are they whom he elected, and that of meer grace and peculiar favour: And then verſ. the 6th. having deſcanted upon this grace, that it ſhuts out works. (Works then are as incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the grace of Election, as with the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58707:7"/>grace of juſtification, with that free favour where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God chuſeth unto life before all time, as with that whereby in time he puts into the ſtate of life, and therefore works fore-ſeen have no more to do in Election, (it being the onely way wherein they in time to be performed, can be repreſented to that degree which prevents all time, then works done, have to do in juſtification) but to return; the Apoſtle having infer'd, that becauſe Election is of grace, it muſt therefore ſhut out works; and this with ſpeciall aime at the errour of the reprobate Jews, who ſtood ſo much upon works: he doth in the 7th verſ. reſume the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, differencing firſt betwixt <hi>Iſrael</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and the Elect of of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> the Election here being the ſame with the remnant according to Election, verſ. 5. Then betwixt the Elect and the reſt from the Elect, by <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the former part of the verſ underſtanding the reſt of <hi>Iſrael</hi> from the Elect in the latter part, who were blinded, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hardened, for ſo the ſame
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>The verb derived ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Callus <hi>then from</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Caecus: <hi>&amp; what if it ſignifie (when blindneſſe) moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly that kind of blindneſs which is by thick filmes and hard ſcales over the eye?</hi>
               </note> word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is otherwhere uſually rendered, <hi>John</hi> 12.40. where it is differenced from this ſignification of blinding, and <hi>Mark</hi> 6.52. it having in it the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of a brawny hardneſſe; and ſo it an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers more expreſly to the Apoſtles Doctrine, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhere, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18.</p>
            <p>The way thus cleared, we have two things to obſerve in the words.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The difference betwixt man and man foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the breaſt of God; ſome are Elect, others the reſt from the Elect, even amongſt his own people. So by outward call; ſome his people whom he fore-knew with the knowledge of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar love; others his people whom he did not fore-know.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58707:7"/>
2. Then different condition for eternall life, who are thus differenced in the breaſt of God; the Elect ſhall certainly have life: <hi>(The Election hath obtained it)</hi> the reſt are hardned unto death. <hi>(And the reſt were hardned)</hi> we ſhall conclude both in this following Doctrine.</p>
            <p>There is this difference between man and man founded in the breaſt of God;
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrin. </seg>
               </label> ſome are choſen to life, and therefore they ſhall moſt certainly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it; others are refuſed to death, whence they ſhall as certainly not eſcape it.</p>
            <p>Before we proceed to confirm the Doctrin, it will be neceſſary to premiſe ſome cautions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In handling this Doctrin, we ſhall be caſt upon the deep things of God, matters of high adoration, even to amazement, for it is a great Myſtery we have in hand: ſo the Apoſtle concludes admiring and adoring, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11 33. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here we muſt beſpeak all ſobriety of ſpirit, with fear and trembling; and indeed there it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves us to beſpeak it, where it is to be had, even at the throne of grace by faithfull prayer.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We ſhall meet with many things to ſtartle humane reaſon, againſt which it will cavill end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly. So <hi>Rom.</hi> 9 14. God is charged with unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and in verſ. 19. with tyranny by mans corrupt reaſon: Here therefore we muſt reſolve ſetting our own wiſdom apart, to follow ſtep by ſtep the Clue of the Word, which alone is able to guide us into this Maze; ſo to hear (what God ſpeaks) though never ſo contrary to our apprehenſions (and affections too) as to ſtop all curious and unwarranted enquiries; and where he makes an end of ſpeaking, there muſt we make an end of enquiring, remembring the incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58707:8"/>greatneſſe of God, and his abſolute domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over us: ſo the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.20.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Many things we are like to meet with, which many are likely moſt dangerouſly to abuſe; ſome to licenciouſneſs, others to inſolent mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings againſt the Lord, and indeed according to this difference betwixt man and man held forth in this Doctrin: this Doctrin it ſelf in the proſecution of it, is like to have a different work, opening the eyes of ſome, ſtriking others blinder then they were; ſoftning ſome, hardning others. But firſt, foraſmuch as God hath in his Word re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed it, we may and muſt enquire into it, onely ſtint our enquiries by the Word.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Myſtery truly conceived is of moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent uſe; the ſpring of true comfort, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of true humility, that which gives light to other Myſteries of the Goſpell, makes very much for clearing the free and peculiar grace of God, which is indeed the life of the Goſpel; is the Maul to beat in pieces, the Rock to ſplit many the moſt dangerous Errours againſt the truth of the Goſpell, and therefore ſo much in all ages op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Devill and his Agents.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is the ſame different fruit of all the truths of God, when they are preached; they are to ſome the favour of life to life, to others, of death to death; yet are we the Miniſters of the Word in preaching of them, unto God a ſweet ſavour in Chriſt, both in them that are ſaved, and in them that periſh.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The children of God muſt not therefore be denyed any part of their food, becauſe the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the wicked one will poyſon themſelves with it; much leſſe muſt they be denyed their chiefeſt food.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:58707:8"/>
Theſe things thus premiſed, we return to the Doctrin, the confirmation whereof depends upon the deſcription; firſt of Election, then of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, as out of the Scriptures they are to be gathered, and by the Scriptures to be opened; But foraſmuch as in the 9th. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> this Myſtery is moſt fully ſpoken to, both for Election and Reprobation, from the firſt to the 24 verſ. and what the Apoſtle here ſpeaks in the 11 Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, hath dependance upon what he had diſputed in the 9th. Chapter, It therefore ſeems very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, briefly to open the Scripture in the firſt place; then to deſcend more particularly to the Doctrine of Election and Reprobation apart, confirming each particular as we go along out of the 9th. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> firſt open'd, adding as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhall be other Scripture Teſtimonies: Now for this Chapter, The Apoſtle prevents and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers the Objection formerly mentioned, as in the 11. Chap. reſumed, which was made againſt the truth of the Goſpell from the Jews rejection of it: in the firſt 23 verſes, ariſing in his anſwer to this great Myſtery, which he firſt aſſerts, and then cleares all the way by propounding and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felling Objections againſt it. In the five firſt verſes, and the former part of the ſixth, we have the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection not in terms propounded, but in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer inſinuated, the ſum of them being this; Though the Jews generally refuſing the Goſpell, fall ſhort of eternall life, and are indeed accurſed from Chriſt; yet the word of the Covenant made betwixt God and them, with their Fathers, ſtands firm, and God fulfills his Covenant to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt; whence it is manifeſt what the Objection is, to which this anſwer is given, the ſame with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58707:9"/>that which was formerly mentioned, <hi>(viz.)</hi> If that be the Goſpell which the Jews refuſe, and by refuſing miſs eternall life, then is the Covenant of God of none effect; in wich objection, there is firſt a ſuppoſition of the Jews rejection. 2. An inference thereupon of Gods unfaithfulneſs.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle grants the ſuppoſition, denyes the inference; grants the ſuppoſition in the five firſt verſes, not expreſly affirming the rejection of the Jews, but rather taking it for granted, expreſſeth his marvellous grief for it, in the three firſt verſes; where obſerve the Apoſtle in the third verſe, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertly ſheweth what is the ſtate of that people, in wiſhing himſelf accurſt from Chriſt for their ſakes; it is as much, as if he had wiſhed himſelf in their ſtead, ſo they might thereby have become Heires of bleſſing; It is impoſſible that man on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhould be mans Redeemer, yet ſo high a ſtrain of love doth the Apoſtle here run, that for the ſalvation of the Jews he would undergoe that wrath, which for man, lay upon mans Redeemer, a love ſo like to the Mediators love was in that breaſt, as ſometimes the like in <hi>Moſes</hi> towards the ſame people; <hi>Moſes</hi> their ſometimes Typicall Mediatour: the Apoſtle having thus expreſſ his griefs, ſhews the ſpeciall reaſons of it, partly his intereſt in them, verſ. the third; partly their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in God, in thoſe many precious priviledges they received peculiarly from God, verſ. the 4th. and 5th. And having thus granted the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, he denyes the inference, verſ. the 6th. <hi>Not as though the word of God had taken none effect;</hi> this word is the word of the Covenant, <hi>I will be thy God and the God of thy ſeed, Gen.</hi> 7.7. as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the following diſcourſe: the meaning
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58707:9"/>then is, the Covenant of God remaines firm, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the generall apoſtacy of the Jews, which the Apoſtle proves by a three-fold inſtance, all tending to this, to limit the Covenant to the true Heirs of it; the firſt inſtance in the poſterity of <hi>Jacob,</hi> the common Father of the Jews; <hi>All are not Iſrael that are of Iſrael;</hi> Iſrael in the firſt place ſignifies <hi>Jacobs</hi> Genuine poſterity, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the purport of the Covenant. In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place, it ſignifies <hi>Jacob</hi> himſelf, the meaning then is; that for <hi>Jacobs</hi> poſterity, all are not faede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally his children, that are his children natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; they are not all his children as he is <hi>Iſrael</hi> (the name of his prevailing with God for the bleſſing) that are his children according to the fleſh; But for light to this and the following inſtances; let us obſerve how a people may be ſaid to be in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God in a double ſence, according to one of which, all <hi>Jacobs</hi> poſterity generally were in Covenant; but according to the other, onely the remnant according to Election: a people therefore may be in Covenant with God. 1. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the outward and common admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of it; ſo all <hi>Jacobs</hi> poſterity was in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, ſeparate by outward call, and ſealed up by Circumciſion to the Lord. 2. According to the ſpeciall and primary intention of it, which is eternall life, and all bleſſings effectuall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; and ſo not all the poſterity of <hi>Jacob</hi> was in Covenant: The former may fall ſhort of life not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that Covenant-intereſt, as not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling the condition of the Covenant; the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cannot; the covenant for them undertaking the condition, and therefore the faithfulneſs of God is engaged not onely to give them life upon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58707:10"/>beleeving, but to give them to believe unto life.</p>
            <p>The ſecond inſtance is in the poſterity of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> who was the head of the Covenant,
<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 12.3. Galat. 3.8.</note> in whom all the families of the earth ſhould be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; here the Apoſtle againe diſtinguiſheth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the naturall, and Faederall off-ſpring, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that ſecond ſence of Covenant-Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, newly laid downe, <hi>Neither becauſe they are the ſeed of Abraham,</hi> (by naturall deſcent) <hi>are they all children,</hi> according to the Covenant, which he proves by Scripture teſtimony, ſetling the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant upon <hi>Iſaac</hi> and his poſterity, excluding <hi>Iſhmael,
<note n="*" place="margin">Chriſt with all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers.</note> But in Iſaac ſhall thy ſeed be called;</hi> then verſe 8. makes an expoſition of that Text of Scripture, where the children of the fleſh are the ſame with the ſeed by naturall deſcent, and the ſeed the ſame with the children of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe or Covenant, <hi>viz.</hi> they in whom the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſhall effectually be made good, and both theſe the ſame with the children of God. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he confirmes his Expoſition, verſe 9. quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.10. the ſumme of his confirmation comes to this; That as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was borne not by the ſtrength of Nature, (for <hi>Abrahams</hi> loynes and <hi>Sarahs</hi> wombe were now dead) but by vertue of the Promiſe, ſo it is with all the faederall off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of <hi>Abraham,</hi> not in that they are from him by naturall deſcent, and therefore not all that naturally deſcend from him, but in that they are his off-ſpring, according to the Promiſe, (and onely to ſome the Promiſe belongs) are they the bleſſed ſeed: The Obſervations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The maine intention of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is eternall life.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They who are the proper ſubjects and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58707:10"/>true heirs of this Covenant, doe effectually ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainlife.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is in the Tenure of this Covenant, not only to give life upon condition, but withall ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to fulfill that condition.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Though the greateſt part of thoſe that are under the outward adminiſtration of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant fall ſhort of life, yet doth the faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God remaine inviolable, foraſmuch as all the true ſubjects and proper heires of the Covenant doe certainly obtaine life.</p>
            <p>Theſe are all cleare from the Objection, that if the Jewes fell from the ſtate of life, the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was void, and the anſwer, preſerving the firmneſſe of the Covenant, in that the proper heires of it have life.</p>
            <p>The third inſtance followes in <hi>Iſaac's</hi> family, in the 10, 11, 12, and 13. verſes, taken out of that Hiſtory, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. v. 23. where firſt the Apoſtle cleares it of thoſe exceptions which might bee made againſt the former inſtance, verſ. 10. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, he layes downe the ſame difference ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſame purpoſe betwixt <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau</hi> the ſonnes of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> that he had formerly laid downe betwixt <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> the ſonnes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> v. 12. &amp; 13. Thirdly, the ground of this difference, verſ. 11. where he opens the great Myſtery of predeſtination.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For exceptions againſt the former inſtance, theſe two might be made: Firſt, <hi>Iſaac</hi> was borne of the free-woman, <hi>Iſhmael</hi> of the bondwoman. Secondly, after <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was borne, was the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the bleſſed ſeed made; and therefore no wonder if the Covenant was ſetled in <hi>Iſaacs</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity only; but it is otherwiſe in <hi>Jacobs</hi> poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58707:11"/>the common Father of the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> theſe exceptions are prevented, verſ. the 10th. <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> were both by one Father, and one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, at one birth; yet as the word of promiſe unto <hi>Sarah,</hi> ſetled it upon <hi>Iſaac</hi> and his poſterity, ſo the word of the Oracle to <hi>Rebecca</hi> upon <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> and his.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The difference is laid down, verſ. 12. where it is manifeſt from the queſtion in hand. 1. That this difference is not ſuch as is common to <hi>Jacob,</hi> with all his poſterity on the one hand, and <hi>Eſau</hi> with all his on the other hand, becauſe it is brought to prove the difference, that hath place in the poſterity of <hi>Jacob</hi> himſelf; <hi>(All are not Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el that are of Iſrael)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is not ſo much a civill as a ſpirituall difference; becauſe that which concludes <hi>Jacob</hi> in the ſaving Covenant, and with him that ſeed of his; that not onely is of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but is <hi>Iſrael;</hi> excludes <hi>Eſau</hi> and his poſterity that Covenant, it being the maine inſtance Vindicating the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of God in making good that Covenant, notwithſtanding the Jews generally fell from the ſtate of life, in as much as the remnant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them obtains life: this difference is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther both confirm'd and cleared, that it is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, (the ſervitude of <hi>Eſau</hi> importing his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion from that Covenant, he in this anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Iſhmael</hi> in the former inſtance) verſ. 13. their different condition proceeding from the Law of God to <hi>Jacob,</hi> and his hatred of <hi>Eſau;</hi> which love and hatred applyed to the queſtion in hand, is manifeſt to be eternall love and hatred, in order to eternall life and death.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle ſingularly taught of God, ſees
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58707:11"/>more in this hatred of God towards <hi>Eſau,</hi> then the deſolation of his earthly inheritance expreſt by the Prophet, 1 <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. Nay in that deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as an outward pledge he reads the Lords eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall hatred, which is yet further manifeſt by the ground of this difference, which now comes to be conſidered.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ground of this difference verſ. 11. where the Apoſtle firſt denyes the ground of this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to be in their works, which he confirms by obſervation of the time, when the teſtimony of their different condition was given; they being yet unborn &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſo denies it to their works, as he aſcribes it unto God; <hi>Not of their workes, but of him,</hi> that is of God; Therefore ſo denyed of their works, as likewiſe of themſelves: the originall and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream ground of their difference not being of themſelves but of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is ſo of God, as that it is of his purpoſe of Election and Reprobation; For the purpoſe of Election it is here laid down; the purpoſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Election, being as much as the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of Election, or that purpoſe whereby God Elects; for the purpoſe of Reprobation, it is here divers waies inſinuated.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the ſpecifying of this purpoſe of Election, which becauſe it is a purpoſe of choyce in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of <hi>Jacob,</hi> muſt therefore be accompanied with a purpoſe of refuſall in regard of <hi>Eſau,</hi> which purpoſe of refuſall, is the purpoſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the removall of works as the ground of their difference, as well evill works denyed the ſupream ground of <hi>Eſau's</hi> ſervitude, as good of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58707:12"/>
               <hi>Jacobs</hi> Dominion, of <hi>Eſau's</hi> hatred, as of <hi>Jacobs</hi> love.</p>
            <p>Therefore another ground muſt be found for <hi>Eſau's</hi> condition, as well as for <hi>Jacobs,</hi> which can be no other then what is hinted concerning <hi>Eſau,</hi> in that which is expreſt concerning <hi>Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The different ſtate and condition of the parties here inſtanced; if onely the purpoſe of Election as it is here expreſt, had been underſtood, well might beloved <hi>Jacob</hi> as the object of it be mentioned; but what place for hated—<hi>Eſau,</hi> in reference to Election? That the Apoſtle then gives this double and contrary inſtance, removes what might be imagined grounds in themſelves from both; (from <hi>Eſau</hi> eſpecially, that which alone might be conceived a ground in him) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the condition of the one expreſly to Gods purpoſe as the originall ground; it muſt needs be that the contrary purpoſe of God, is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the originall ground of the others conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; hitherto, that it is not of works, that it is of God; that it is ſo of God, as of his purpoſe of Election and Reprobation: Now follows, 4. It is ſo of the purpoſe of Election (on <hi>Jacobs</hi> part) as that <hi>it may
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> abide.</hi> And therefore 5ly. So of God according to the purpoſe of Election, <hi>as of him that calleth;</hi> in our Call we receive faith, and that renewing worke of the ſpirit, whereby we are brought into the ſtate of life; it is then ſo of God according to the purpoſe of Election, as of him that by vertue of that purpoſe gives faith, and brings into the ſtate of life, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of the holy Ghoſt; and thus his Election remaines firme for the iſſue of it, eternall life to the Elect, as borrowing nothing, depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58707:12"/>on nothing in man, but undertaking and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all: hence it is manifeſt, when the Apoſtle ſhuts out works, he ſhuts out as wel works foreſeen as done, becauſe expreſly for Election; ſo denyes it to be of works, as that it ſhall be of God; but if of works foreſeen, it was of our ſelves, ſo of God as of his purpoſe, which (we ſhall ſee by and by) cannot be built upon any thing but himſelf; ſo of his purpoſe as that it may abide without change, and therefore muſt have a ſurer foundation then works fore-ſeen, or indeed any thing foreſeen in man: and therefore ſo of God according to his purpoſe, as of him that calls; therefore ſhuts out not works onely, but faith too; faith not onely acted but fore-ſeen. 1. It is not thus, not of works, but of him that believe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; but not of works, but of God. 2. Nor thus; not of works, but of him that juſtifieth; but thus, not of works, but of him that calleth; juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication ſuppoſeth faith, in our call we receive faith; it is then of God according to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of Election, not as of him that fore-ſees ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther works or faith, but as of him that gives faith; and therefore cannot fore-ſee it antecedently to his purpoſe, but in his purpoſe of giving it: And now that the fore-light of evill works, or of any thing in man, is not the firſt ground of his peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing condition; but in <hi>Eſau's</hi> caſe evill works fore-ſeen have no more to do, then wrought, as to the point in hand we ſhall make it appear in theſe two Concluſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the different purpoſe of God electing ſome, refuſing others; in the firſt ground of their different ſtate, who embracing the truth are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and who rejecting the truth are damned.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:58707:13"/>
2. That this purpoſe is not built, doth not ſtand nor depend upon any thing in man, but is wholly of it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Concluſions as they are clearly to be made good from the Apoſtles diſcourſe hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſo will the confirmation of them make good the thing in hand.</p>
            <p>For the firſt we have ſeen it in <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> and they are ſpeciall inſtances to conclude the generall queſtion about the Jews, the Nation generally refuſing the Goſpell, and ſo periſhing, the remnant imbracing it, and ſo obtaining life, as is clear by the Apoſtles diſcourſe, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward he enlargeth to all mankind.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, (ſetting aſide that the Apoſtle hath carryed the purpoſe of Election and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, in a parrallel ſtrain) let theſe arguments conclude it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whatſoever is done, God either doth it as the firſt worker, or permits it to be done, as the ſupream Ruler. 'Tis clear, if God will neither have an hand in doing it, nor ſuffer it to be done, it cannot be done;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Enchrid. ad laurent. c.</hi> 95.</note> Nothing is done without the will of the Almighty that it ſhould be done, he either ſuffering it to be done, or himſelf do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; <hi>Auguſtine</hi> further, whatſoever is permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be done, as the evill of ſinne, requires ſome concourſe of God, <hi>(In whom we live, and move, and have our being)</hi> for production of that act, to which as by man done, ſinne cleaves inſeparably; otherwiſe ſecond cauſes in producing their acts, ſhould move independently upon the firſt cauſe, and the Creature ſhould Create.</p>
            <p>Therefore onely ſo far doth God fore-ſee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all time, what ſhall be in time, as he ſees his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58707:13"/>owne will, either for the doing it, or permitting it to be done, for affoording that concourſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which it cannot be done.</p>
            <p>The will of God then before all time, that is, his decree or purpoſe for the being of ſuch or ſuch a thing in time muſt be the ground of his fore-ſight that it ſhall be, and therefore in order of nature before it, and ſo his purpoſe meerly of himſelfe: For ſtill whatſoever can be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned fore-ſeen, as that which ſhall be, to move his will, that it may be fore-ſeen, as that which ſhall be, muſt of neceſſity ſuppoſe his will that it ſhall be.</p>
            <p>For further clearing this truth, (though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is a truth that ſhines ſo clearly in its own light, as well might forbid all further clearing) conſider, of things that are not; Some are only poſſible, and may be, <hi>(God can raiſe up children to Abraham of the ſtones;)</hi> Some are future, and ſhall be, both knowne to God: But how is this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge differenced? All things poſſible he knowes in his owne power; all things future in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if God fore-ſee what ſhall be, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of nature before his decree that it ſhall be, otherwiſe then in his decree, then is he diſpoiled of all liberty, both in his decree, and for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree. 1. In his decree; if he will decree, he hath his rule before-hand from the creature, what he fore-ſees antecedently to his decree ſhall bee; therefore becauſe it ſhall be, doth he fore-ſee that it ſhall be, then hath he no liberty left to decree otherwiſe, but either his decree muſt be fruſtrate, or contradictions muſt be true; Such a thing ſhall be, and therefore God hath fore-ſeen that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58707:14"/>it ſhall be; the ſame thing ſhall not be, God hath decreed that it ſhall not be: But for as much as both theſe cannot be true, God muſt be content to ſtand under the moſt fatall neceſſity that is imaginable; The ſum of the Stoick fate was,
<note n="*" place="margin">Once hee comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes.</note> 
               <hi>Semel juſſit, ſemper paret,</hi> here it is <hi>Nunquam juſsit, ſemper paret;</hi> he muſt obey what is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the creature, even there where ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is fatall bondage in the determination of his will, how unſeaſonably are the adverſaries of the truth wont to raiſe clamours againſt that neceſſity which man ſtands under upon ſuppoſall of Gods decree? That ſecond cauſes ſhould by the firſt cauſe be determined, ſo as upon ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the firſt cauſes predetermination, to work only to that iſſue which is predetermined, (the ſame conditionall neceſsity being undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble upon their own ſuppoſition of fore-ſight:) In the mean time for the manner of their workings, rational &amp; free agents left free in their working, the ſame decree that determines them to one iſſue, determining them likewiſe to work freely to that iſſue; all this is orderly and faire: The firſt cauſe herein having its due preheminence, the ſecond cauſe in due ſubjection, yet without all impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but to lay the firſt cauſe under the ſeconds foot, and that when in its weakeſt ſtate; not in being, but that which ſhall be, is to raze the everlaſting foundations: Thus is God diſpoiled of liberty in his decree. Secondly, What liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath he for it? Such a thing ſhall be, is ſo fore-ſeen of him before his decree; what place is there now for his decree? in his decree he playes but an after-game, it will be, whether he decree or no; how is this beſeeming the Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58707:14"/>to decree that which is ſure enough to be, before he determine any ſuch thing? To what end is ſuch a decree?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by the different condition of men, according to Gods different purpoſe of Election and Reprobation, is God finally and eternally glorified; if then God hath not determined meerly of the Counſell of his owne Will, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his purpoſe within himſelfe, their difference with the whole order of it; he hath not of himſelfe determined his owne ſtate of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glory, but it comes to paſſe occaſionally from the creature, as he light upon it peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, according to the uncertaine working of the ſickle creature, it is ſo now, it might have been otherwiſe: <hi>Adam</hi> fell, ſo way was made for the eternall manifeſtation of Gods revenging Juſtice, and ſparing mercy in Chriſt, he might have ſtood for ought that God determined, and ſo, for ought that he determined, ſuch a way of glorifying himſelfe might not have been; ſo all the great workes, mans finall ſtate, Gods finall glory, the giving of Chriſt, the whole method of ſalvation by Chriſt, are occaſionall from the creature, not originally from the Counſells of God, but as the creature hapt to put him upon theſe things: But is there any thing more prime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clear both in Scripture and to true Reaſon, then that the firſt things in Gods aime in order to all his workes is his glory? Did he not make all things for himſelfe? Are not all things of him, from him, to him? Is not he the ſupreme great, and therefore all things muſt be ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to his glory? Is he not the ſupreme good, and therefore lovely above all? therefore loves
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58707:15"/>himſelfe above all? therefore makes and orders all things for his owne glory? There is a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall obligation of juſtice to himſelfe whereby he cannot but ſet up his own glory, as the white to which all his workes ſhall be directed, that then being firſt in his eye, as the end of all, and that way whereby he is unto all eternity glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, being pitch't in his counſells, he muſt needs order and adminiſter all things making there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and therefore by vertue of his owne glory decreed, he decrees the whole Series from the firſt ſtep to the laſt tending thereto. Hence then it is manifeſt, that this purpoſe of his for the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ſtate of man, it is meerly of it ſelfe, above all works good or evill, faith or unbeliefe, above the fore-ſight of all, comprehending theſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it, appointing and ordering them; which will yet be further cleare by the Apoſtles diſcourſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:58707:15"/>
            <head>THE SECOND SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 11.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But the Election hath obtained it, and the reſt were hardned.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ver.</hi> 14. <hi>to the</hi> 19.</bibl> 
                     <hi>followes an Objection, with the Anſwer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Objection, ver. 14. the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle knowing how endleſly the fleſh will cavill againſt this truth, layes down and prevents an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection here, <hi>What ſhall we ſay then, is there unrighteouſneſſe with God?</hi> This is the charge of mans corrupt reaſoning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, ariſing from the Doctrine of Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtination.</p>
            <p>The ſumme of the Objection is this: If God deal ſo unequally with them that in themſelves are equall, then is he unrighteous, but according to the Apoſtles Doctrine ſo it is; for their works good or evill come not at all into account with God as Motives to his Will one way or other for his decree; therefore he is unrighteous.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:58707:16"/>
For anſwer; 1. The Apoſtle deteſts the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of the propoſition. Though God deale ſo unequally (in regard of his decree) with thoſe that in themſelves are equall, yet far be that blaſphemy from any to charge him with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He Vindicates the righteouſneſs of God: 1. In points of Election, verſ. 15.16. Verſ. 15. By that ſoveraigne liberty which God hath for willing, and decreeing mercy to whom he pleaſes, meerly becauſe he pleaſes, for which he quotes <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.19. whence verſ. 16. he laies down a generall concluſion; <hi>So then it is not,</hi> &amp;c. the meaning; it is not by any, either good deſires in man <hi>(it is not in him that willeth)</hi> or good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of man, <hi>(it is not in him that runneth)</hi> that God is prevented in his decree, but his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree is wholly of it ſelf; for mercy, becauſe he will have mercy; <hi>(But of God that ſheweth mercy.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In point of reprobation, the Apoſtle ſhewes the ſame Liberty of proceeding meerly according to the will of God in the inſtance of <hi>Pharoah,</hi> for which he quotes <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.16. and thence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a full and equall liberty in God, both for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection and Reprobation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the inſtance of <hi>Pharoah</hi> verſ. 17. Two things are affirmed. 1. That God raiſed him up, which comprehends his bringing into the world, his preſervation, his advancement to the Throne, his ſingling out to ſtand in oppoſition againſt the Lord, his obfirmation in that wickedneſſe of his —2. The end of it, that God by powerfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying ſuch a wicked Tyrant, might glorifie his great name.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Now that God made uſe thereof the ſame
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58707:16"/>liberty appears: Firſt by the connexive particle <hi>(for)</hi> which relating to the former verſes, where that Liberty had been aſſerted inſinuates here the like. 2. By the concluſion, verſ. 18. which avouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſame liberty here as formerly in Election; and the Apoſtle drawing this concluſion for that part of it which concerns Reprobation, from the 17. verſ. as appears by the illative particle <hi>(there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore)</hi> he gives us to underſtand, that what is ſaid of Gods raiſing up <hi>Pharoah</hi> is ſo to be conceived, as that therein that ſoveraigne liberty whereby God proceeds meerly according to his will is imported.</p>
            <div type="observations">
               <head>Obſervations.</head>
               <p n="1">1. From the Objection; How hardly fleſh and blood reliſheth the true Doctrin of Predeſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it will rather riſe up to a peremptory and blaſphemous charge of unrighteouſneſſe againſt the Lord then yield to it. The pride of man will not endure the true Doctrine of juſtification, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the pride nor guilt of man the truth of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination; hence in all ages is found ſo much oppoſition, in St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> time by the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> after him by their ſucceſſors; ſince the time of Reformation, <hi>Stapleton, Bellarmine,</hi> and the whole Nation of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> with other perverſe Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, as <hi>Caſtellio</hi> againſt <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Beza. Arminius</hi> againſt <hi>Perkins;</hi> and now the Hereticks of our times, who have made a compound of the former Errors againſt this truth.</p>
               <p>From the Objection and the anſwer together.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Apoſtle laid down as well the Doctrine of Reprobation as of Election, in the former verſes; becauſe this Objection thence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58707:17"/>takes in both, and the anſwer Vindicates God in both.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That what was formerly taught by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in the inſtance of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> for the dependance of their different condition origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally on the decree of God, concerns not onely themſelves and the Jews, but all men, becauſe here are generall concluſions laid down, verſ. 16 18. and in <hi>Pharoah</hi> an inſtance of ſuch as are out of the Church, ſo that all the world as well as they of the viſible Church, are differenced by Gods decree.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That neither workes good or evill, faith or unbelief, ſo much as foreſeen prevented the decree of God, but were prevented by it; for if ſo, 1. There had been no place for this objection, the Apoſtle in ſtating it, teacheth us his meaning in the 11th v. to ſhut out all reſpects in the Creature If God loved <hi>Jacob</hi> upon faith or good works foreſeen, hated <hi>Eſau</hi> upon unbelief, or evil works foreſeen, here had been no place, no not ſo much as for corrupt reaſon to queſtion Gods righteouſneſſe; for then had he dealt unequally, not with thoſe who were equall, but unequall in his ſight.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the anſwer to the Objection, it Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates the Lord upon another ground, his ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne power of dealing with man herein meerly according to his will; how eaſily had the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors mouth been ſtopt by mentioning their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent qualifications fore-ſeen, if that had been the truth?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whatſoever the Scripture holds forth for the will of God, we are thence to conclude it juſt, or (if it ariſe above the reſpects of juſtice in the uſuall ſenſe, which ſuppoſeth an object of reward)
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58707:17"/>at the leaſt not unjuſt: So the Apoſtle, becauſe it is Gods will to have mercy on whom he will, and harden whom he will; that is to ordain whom he will unto mercy, and whom he will unto wrath hardning thereunto; this ordination of his ariſing above all good or evill, ſo much as fore-ſeen in the Creature, he therefore concludes it juſt; ſuppoſe we can no more comprehend the righteouſneſſe of God in ſuch away of his, then we can the myſtery of the Trinity; we muſt not therefore denie it to be his will, becauſe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fathom the righteouſneſs thereof, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Scripture affirms it his will, we muſt conclude it righteous.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That not onely comparative Predeſtination is above all different reſpects in the creature, but ſingle above all reſpects, whether in Election or Reprobation,</p>
               <p>Some grant that thus far it is clear in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles diſcourſe, that <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> were equal, as repreſented to the decree of God; and what diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence was betwixt them flowed originally from the decree, and therefor God in chuſing one, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the other proceeded meerly according to his wil, that if the queſtion be, why did he chuſe <hi>Iacob</hi> rather then <hi>Eſau?</hi> or why did he refuſe <hi>Eſau</hi> rather then <hi>Iacob?</hi> no other anſwer is to be given but meerly his will: This for comparative Election and Reprobation, but then for ſingle; they think there is in all men a neceſſary qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one and the ſame; the conſideration whereof is in order of nature, before the decree either of Election or Reprobation, and that is the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of nature over all men, all alike; hence they make the object of Predeſtination man fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58707:18"/>not comprehending within it, the creation and the fall, but ſtating it below both.</p>
               <p>Againſt this opinion, the three arguments for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly uſed to prove the purpoſe of God to be wholly of it ſelf, will conclude; we ſhall have further occaſion to diſcuſſe this more fully upon the next verſes; for the preſent, let us ſee how far what the Apoſtle hath here argued makes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, concluding rather the decree of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination to ariſe above both the fall and the Creation, and to have for it's object, man not as yet Created, in divine conſideration.</p>
               <p n="1">1. From the Objection; there had been little reaſon for it, had fallen and ſinfull man been the Object; For when all had deſerved to periſh, what colour of unrighteouſneſs was there, that God ſhould decree the ſaving of ſome in mercy, leaving others to periſh according to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert?</p>
               <p n="2">2. From the anſwer; The Apoſtles anſwer is from Gods ſoveraigne liberty of diſpoſing of man according to his Will: but had fallen man been the object, an anſwer more ſatisfying the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, leſſe lyable to exception had been ready at hand to this purpoſe; for as much as all men have deſerved to dye, had God ſo determined of all he had been juſt, that he ordaines ſome to life, it is his mercy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. From the following diſcourſe which clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſetteth forth man as not yet created to be the object, raiſing this decree of God above both the fall and the creation; and being the continuance of the Apoſtles former diſcourſe, concludes the Apoſtles meaning the ſame, in the former diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:58707:18"/>
Verſe 19. <hi>Why doth he yet complaine? who hath reſiſted his will?</hi> The meaning, by what right doth God find fault with man, and puniſh him for his ſin, foraſmuch as it is his will to harden him in ſin? the former Objection chargeth God with unrighteouſneſs; this with tyranny. For an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The will of God is his <hi>Decreeing</hi> will.</item>
                  <item>The will of God is his <hi>declaring</hi> will.</item>
               </list>
               <p>His decreeing will determines what ſhall be; his declaring will ſhews, 1. What is mans duty. 2. What God accepts when it is performed; it is here the decreeing will which no man can reſiſt, his declaring will is ſo often reſiſted, as ſinne is committed; and the ſtrength of the objection is in this, that man in reſiſting his declaring will, <hi>viz.</hi> what he commands, and in the performance whereof he would be well pleaſed; doth yet not reſiſt his decreeing will, ſo the Objection clearly formed is this; If God have decreed that man ſhall ſin and be hardned in his ſins, and no man can reſiſt this decree of God; by what right can he puniſh man for his ſin? For anſwer, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle grants what the objection alleadgeth; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes what it would conclude, by pleading Gods abſolute ſoveraignty over man; and in his ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, his liberty for diſpoſing of man, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to his will, his will no way taking riſe from any thing in man; and this by checking the inſolency of man in thus conteſting with his Creator, forgetfull of his Dominion over him, which by compariſon is illuſtrated verſ. 20. and and this compariſon ſpecified, and further clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by inſtance of the Potter and his clay, ver. 21.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58707:19"/>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1 1</cell>
                        <cell>1 1</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Potter, God.</cell>
                        <cell>The Clay, Mankind.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2.</cell>
                        <cell>2.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Potters power over the Clay.</cell>
                        <cell>Gods Dominion over man.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3.</cell>
                        <cell>3.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Clay in the lump not yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into Veſſels.</cell>
                        <cell>Mankinde not as yet Created.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4.</cell>
                        <cell>4.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of the ſame lump.</cell>
                        <cell>Of mankind equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repreſented.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5.</cell>
                        <cell>5.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>One Veſſel to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, another made to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</cell>
                        <cell>One man created for eternall life, another for the day of evill.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Now let us ſee from this Objection, and the anſwer to it; whether man fallen, or man not yet created, be the Object of Predeſtination? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſin of the firſt man, and in him the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of all men be conſidered before the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree? or whether the decree of God comprehend within it, the ſin both of the firſt man, and of all men; this by certain ſteps.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The objection taking for granted, that men are hardned in ſin according to the decreeing wil of God, it is not denyed by the Apoſtle, but juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: but whether doth the conſideration of ſin
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58707:19"/>in the parties to be hardned, move God to that decree of hardning them; or doth that ſin for which they are hardned, fall within the decree of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Though God fore-ſee that they ſhall fin before, he will harden them in their ſinne, their hardning being a judgement upon them for their ſin; yet doth not the fore-ſight of that ſinne go before his decree of hardning in ſin, but he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of his meer pleaſure. 1. To permit them to ſin, in order to hardning. 2. To harden them in ſin order in to condemnation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Otherwiſe there was no place for this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, for it is granted on all Hands, that upon ſin committed it is juſt with God to harden, and it will follow by like reaſon, that upon the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of ſin to be committed; and this without the decree of God, it may be juſt with God to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree to harden; and there is no more colour of objecting againſt God in this latter, then in the former.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Neither otherwiſe doth it ſuite to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles former diſcourſe; the decree whereby God wills the hardning of the Reprobate, is the ſame with that whereby he hated <hi>Eſau,</hi> as is clear by the thread of the Apoſtles diſcourſe, from verſ. 13 to 19. but that riſeth above all reſpect of ſin to be committed, v. 11.</p>
               <p>Hitherto we have gained this ſtep, that thoſe actuall ſins in recompence whereof, by the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous judgement of God, the Reprobates are hardned unto death, fall within the decree of God, are not fore-ſeen without his decree, as Motives to his decree, but are by him decreed with intention of hardning for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:58707:20"/>
But then ſecondly, Doth not the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of naturall corruption by the fall, go before this decree of God, and thence the juſtice of God more clear, that though he decrees to permit to ſin in order to hardning; yet is it onely ſinfull man ſo conſidered in his decree, fallen into a ſtate of ſin without his decree, that he ſo decrees to permit to ſin?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> But then ſtill what place for the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection?</p>
               <p>That God may harden men for ſins commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted is granted on all hands, that he is not bound to recover fallen man; but may leave him to commit thoſe ſins for which he is hardned, is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe granted, that he may find fault with, &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh with eternal wrath hardned ſinners, is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe granted, ſuppoſing then the corruption of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the eye of God before his decree of hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Reprobate; there is no place for this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, except we ſhall ſay that God muſt decree either not to ſuffer fallen man further to ſin, or not to harden any ſinners in ſin, or not to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh hardned ſinners; but this is contrary to what by all is granted.</p>
               <p>Thus far the Objection makes for man, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as not yet created, to be the Object of Predeſtination.</p>
               <p>Now for the Anſwer: It will make it yet more clear. Where 1. The Apoſtle pleads Gods abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute power over man, by right of Creation, verſ. 20.21. 2. Expoſtulates for further clearing, 1. The ſpeciall end. 2. The righteous execution of his decree, v. 22.23.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He pleads his abſolute power and ſoveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or dominion, verſ. 20. who art thou that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58707:20"/>again, by way of conteſtation with God: God is ſo far above thee, and hath that Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over thee, that he is not lyable to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what he doth concerning thee.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This power over man, not as created (much leſs fallen) but as to be created: ſhall the thing formed, fay to him that formed it, why haſt thou <hi>mademe thus?</hi> We here ſee by the Apoſtles anſwer, the mind of the Objection, which was to charge God with Tyranny: that he decrees to harden the Reprobate in ſin, upon ſuppoſall that this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of his riſeth above the conſideration of man as created; and in his decree of Creation, he hath this intention: <hi>Why haſt thon made me thus?</hi> which is yet more expreſly in the next words, what power the Potter hath to make Veſſels for different uſe, honourable or diſhonourable: the ſame power hath God to Create men, ſome for ſalvation, others for deſtruction, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4.</p>
               <p>Now ſuppoſe man fallen had been the Object, a ready and ſatisfying anſwer had been rather from Gods righteouſneſs then dominion: to this effect, that though God decrees to harden to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate in ſin, yet he ſees them firſt as ſinners, and that without his decrees.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He decrees to harden them in a certain or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. 1. Not to recover them from their ſinfull ſtate, but ſuffer them to multiply their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions. 2. To harden them by way of righteous judgement for thoſe tranſgreſſions of theirs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this order of the decree; that it takes it uſe from the ſin of man antecedently to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree; the plea of Gods righteouſneſs muſt clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have ſatisfied even a cavilling adverſary,: for who can doubt but when man hath fallen with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58707:21"/>his decree, God is not bound to recover him from ſin; or that when his tranſgreſſions are mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied, the Lord may not harden him, that is, with-hold ſuch workes of his Spirit as he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly afforded him, after ſinfull mans manifold abuſe of them, and deliver him up fully to his own heart and Satan. That alone which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the plea of Gods power is, that the firſt ſtep here is according to Gods decree, and his decree of Creation is accompanied with this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: It is well obſerved by learned <hi>Camero,</hi> that for the properties of God, ſome of them are converſant about the object already conſtituted, ſuch are his mercy and juſtice, ſome about the conſtitution of the object, ſuch are his wiſdome and power, the power of God is here ſo pleaded, not as ſuppoſing man created and fallen in the knowledge of God, but to be created and to fall by the decree of God; the apprehenſion then of man conſidered as ſinfull, to be the object of this decree, it is firſt againſt the nature of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles argument here, which is power, or domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not juſtice.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is againſt the proſecution of it; 1. <hi>Shall the thing formed ſay to him that formed it, Why haſt thou made me thus?</hi> according to that concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſhould have been thus rather, <hi>Shall the thing deformed ſay to him that formed it, Why haſt thou mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me thus?</hi> 2. Hath not the Potter power of the ſame lump, &amp;c.?</p>
               <p n="1">1. They who will have the difference to ariſe from faith or workes fore-ſeen, ſuppoſe here not one and the ſame lump, but two, and thoſe very different lumps.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They that will have man as fallen, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58707:21"/>of Predeſtination, will not allow the Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter power to make veſſells for diſhonour of any other lump then that which is firſt corrupt and marred, juſt contrary to the purport of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument; Where is the Potters power then over his clay?</p>
               <p>Thus we have ſeen from this Objection and Anſwer to it, man conſidered as not yet created, the object of Predeſtination: Let us now adde another Argument from the Angells.</p>
               <p>The purpoſe of Election and Reprobation for the Angells hath them for the object as not created, or it is of workes; one of theſe two muſt needs be, becauſe there is not in any one Angell fallen the corruption and fall of the reſt, as in man; but that it ſhould be of workes is to be denied upon the ſame grounds that it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied for man, they that grant that in man it is not of workes, yet will have man conſidered as fallen the object, are here troubled to extricate themſelves; for if it carry with it many abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that mans Election or Reprobation ſhould be of Workes or Faith ſo much as fore-ſeen, as they grant it doth, the ſame muſt likewiſe be granted in caſe of the Angels for works.</p>
               <p>If it may without abſurdity be granted for the Angells, that they are to be conſidered in the purpoſe of God as to be created, then may it likewiſe in man, and if it may it muſt, for the Scriptures ſound cleare enough that way, onely they, for avoyding as they thinke, ſome abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, interpret them another way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:58707:22"/>
               <head>Let us adde another Argument to clear the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of abſolute power in this point.</head>
               <p>If in another caſe of equall concernment the Lord proceeds according to his abſolute power, then without all abſurdity is it to be granted here; but ſo it is: For inſtance.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The imputation of <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne to all his Poſterity; By what rule of regulated juſtice am I (conceived in the womb five or ſix thouſand years after <hi>Adams</hi> ſin) charged with that ſin of his? Would this be warrantable betwixt man and man, that by the Fathers offence againſt his Prince, all his ſucceeding Poſterity throughout all generations ſhould be liable to death? Or indeed any of them who were not ſo much as borne or conceived when the Father committed his treſpaſſe? Will it be ſaid in caſe ſuch a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant be made, it is warrantable? But by what rule may ſuch a Covenant be made? or if made, how not more warrantably broken then kept?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Imputation of mans ſin to Chriſt, and in him puniſhing the ſinnes of all the Elect: Might any Prince hang, draw, and quarter the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and noble Peere in the Kingdom, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Kingdomes heire, and the ſonne of his loynes, thereby to acquit a company of wretched Traytors? Yet all this moſt juſt in God, becauſe he hath this abſolute power over man, and even over the humane nature of Chriſt, that Chriſt was willing to undergo this, alters not the caſe in point of juſtice, for hereunto he as man, was appointed and created by the Father, and if it had been poſſible that Chriſt, as man, could have
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58707:22"/>refuſed it, he had therein ſinned.</p>
               <p>What is it then that carries ſo many to pitch upon the corrupt Maſſe?</p>
               <p n="1">1. A meer fallacy, for as much as Election is a decree of mercy, Reprobation of juſtice; the one for ſaving, the other for condemning fallen and ſinfull man; therefore here is ſinne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered before the decree, ſparing mercy, and condemning juſtice, neceſſarily ſuppoſing finne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. All that can hence be concluded is, that the decree determines that ſin ſhall be before either the ſalvation of the Elect, or the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Reprobate; but not that the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of ſinne as that which ſhall be, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the decree, or the fore-ſight of it a motive to the Decree it ſelfe; ſee a cleare inſtance: The decree of Election is a decree of ſaving all and onely perſevering believers, (for thoſe of years;) of Reprobation for condemning all and onely impenitent ſinners; therefore ſalvation ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth finall perſeverance in faith, and condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion finall impenitency in ſin, and that according to the decree, yet the decree it ſelfe doth not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them, and take its riſe from them, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends them, and ordaines them, otherwiſe it was of works, (faith in this conſideration put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the nature of works, as making the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be of the called rather then of the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler) contrary to the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. v. 11. This miſtake ſuppoſeth whatſoever is required to the execution of the decree in the laſt act of it, muſt before-ſeen without and before the decree as a motive to it, whereas the decree it ſelfe ordaines whatſoever makes for the execution of it in the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58707:23"/>laſt act. Another familiar inſtance: A man pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth to leave his name behinde him when he dies in a legitimate off-ſpring, this cannot be without a wife; now according to that miſtake he muſt fore-ſee that he ſhall have a wife before he purpoſeth any ſuch thing, and the fore-ſight hereof muſt be a motive to him for purpoſing ſo to leave his name in his Poſterity; whereas it is clear in true conſideration, that becauſe he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth ſo to leave his name, he therefore purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to take a wife, nor doth he any other way ſee before-hand that he ſhall have a wife then in his owne purpoſe: That decree which determines the end, comprehends likewiſe the meanes to that end, otherwiſe it would be a decree to no end, a purpoſe to no purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe the ſinne of man is in order of time before either his ſalvation, or condemnation, that God might be glorified in his ſparing mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon ſome, in his revenging juſtice upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; therefore muſt that intention of his ſinne be in order of nature after Gods intention of ſo glorifying himſelfe, for whatſoever makes for the accompliſhment of the end, as the meanes thereto, is appointed in order to, and by vertue of the end it ſelfe fore-appointed. Hence that well knowne rule, What is firſt in intention, is laſt in execution; Inſtance, A man builds an houſe in ſuch a place, of ſuch a forme, of ſo many roomes for himſelfe to dwell in, the laſt thing here in execution is his dwelling in the houſe, but it was the firſt in his intention, and therefore for the conveniency of his dwelling did he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide materials, build it in ſuch a place, in ſuch a forme, &amp;c. Hence if God fore-ſee the ſinne of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58707:23"/>man, as that which ſhould be, before he decreed the glorifying himſelfe in the ſalvation or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of ſinfull man, then did he intend to permit ſin (without which permiſſion it could not be, and therefore without the intention to permit it, could not be fore-ſeen) before he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ſo to glorifie himſelfe, but the permiſſion of ſin being firſt in intention, muſt be laſt in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution; therefore man muſt firſt be condemned or ſaved, and then permitted to ſinne: So great an abſurdity doth that miſtake run upon.</p>
               <p>Therefore to conclude; 1. Election is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree for ſparing niercy, Reprobation for reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging juſtice, rather then of them, each of them being an act of abſolute and arbitrary power, favouring or refuſing to favour, meerly at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Yet there is a twofold juſtice in God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Towards himſelfe, whereby he doth for himſelfe whatſoever his wiſdome dictates to be for his owne glory.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Towards the creature, whereby he diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth good or evill to it upon certaine condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>In the former ſenſe Election and reprobation both are acts of juſtice, God is to be juſtified in whatſoever he doth beſeeming his wiſdome for his glory.</p>
               <p>In the latter ſenſe they are for juſtice and mercy, rather then of them. This for the firſt ground of that miſtake.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A needleſſe feare; they are afraid to affirm that God decreed and willed the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> leſt they ſhould thereby make him the Author of ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:58707:24"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To be the Author of ſinne is ſo to act as to ſtand under the guilt of ſinne, to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the guilt of ſinne ſuppoſeth ſubjection to a law againſt which we act: Now let ſuch a law be ſhewed againſt which God offends in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that man (take it of the firſt man, and his firſt ſin) ſhall ſin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Doth not God will the fall of <hi>Adam?</hi> How then?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Is it againſt his Will? But he is Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is it without his Knowledge? But he is Omniſcient.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Is it beſide his Will? But 1. Not one hair from the head, nor a ſparrow to the ground, nor the iſſue of the lot in the lap without his diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. 2. Then did he not determine what ſhould be the end of man, when he intended to create him, nor what his courſe; by the ſame reaſon the ſame is to be ſaid for the Angells, nor how he would be glorified in the ſmall ſtate of men and Angells, nor the giving of Chriſt, nor the Goſpell in the world, the whole Oeconomy of mans ſalvation and condemnation, of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God here, and in heaven, of redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Chriſt, and thereupon his glory, all origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally beſide the will of God ordered occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally: I had as lieve ſubſcribe to that wilde Philoſophie which teacheth the world to be made of the caſuall concourſe of Atomes, as to this more wild Theologie, which teacheth the whole adminiſtration of this world, and that to come, to come about meerly caſually and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionally.</p>
               <p>We have formerly upon <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. v. 11. in the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58707:24"/>firſt Sermon laid down three arguments, proving the purpoſe of God to be meerly of it ſelfe, which will here fully conclude that both the ſin of the firſt man, and all ſins whatſoever are decreed by God, let us forme them to this particular.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He decrees to permit ſinne, (otherwiſe he could not ſo much as fore-ſee it, as was there manifeſted; againe, whereas he in time permits it, if he did not before all time will to permit it, it is with him according to mans weakneſſe, counſells ariſe in his breſt a new) therefore he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees that ſin ſhall be upon his permiſſion, the permiſſion of ſinne cannot be conceived to have no further end, but that it ſhould reſt meerly in the act of permiſſion, and indeed the permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſin doth involve the being of it upon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
               <p>Further, foraſmuch as there is no evill but in good, and in every ſinfull act we have to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the act, and the ſin cleaving to the act, the act and that which is good he works, who is the firſt cauſe, the fountaine of being and goodneſſe, in whom we move, the ſin cleaving to the act he permits: Hence in <hi>Joſephs</hi> ſale by his brethren, the crucifying of Chriſt, the deſpoiling <hi>Job</hi> of all he had, &amp;c. the will and the hand of God are owned; If God had not willed the crucifying of Chriſt, (and what greater ſinne?) how had he willed the ſalvation of man by Chriſt? which yet he willed from all eternity, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4. Again, if God willed not the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> (and it the mother ſinne) how did he will the ſalvation of man by Chriſt? it being the firſt ſtep making way thereto; this leads to the</p>
               <p n="2">2. He that from all eternity wills that end
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58707:25"/>which cannot be brought to paſſe without the being of ſinne, he wills that ſinne ſhall be, but God wills that end, the glorifying his ſparing mercy tempered with his juſtice in Chriſt, in the ſalvation of ſome, his revenging juſtice in the condemnation of others; and this way of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying himſelfe neceſſarily ſuppoſeth ſinne, there being no place for that kind either of mercy or juſtice without ſinne; therefore he wills that ſin ſhall be, and the firſt ſinne as well as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without which the other had not been: Hence</p>
               <p n="3">3. Though ſin be not good but evill, yet that ſinne ſhould be it is good, good foraſmuch as it is neceſſarily conducible to his glory, he having ſet downe in the counſell of his Will in ſuch a way to be glorified, but God wills all good, therefore he wills that ſinne ſhall be: Sin is evil, therefore it falls not under the Will of God to approve it, that ſin ſhould be is good, therefore it falls under the Will of God to decree it. Hence
<note n="*" place="margin">Enchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid. c. 69.</note> S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> It is not to be doubted but God doth well, even in ſuffering to be done whatſoever things are evilly done; for this he ſuffers not but by a righteous judgement, and truly whatſoever is righteous is good, although therefore thoſe things which are evill, in as much as they are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill are not good; yet that not only thoſe things which are good, but which are evill too, ſhould be, is good:
<note n="*" place="margin">Enchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid. c. 100.</note> Whence after a wonderfull and unſpeakable manner, it is not brought to paſſe beſide his Will, that even againſt his Will is brought to paſſe not beſide his Will decreeing, which is againſt his Will approving.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For that Argument taken from the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58707:25"/>of God both in and for his decree, apply it here to his Will, when he permits ſinne, whether the firſt ſin, or any other, and it will conclude his will neceſſarily determined beforehand by the creature, except we will grant, that he freely of himſelfe decreed thoſe ſins to be; many other Arguments might be added. As,</p>
               <p n="5">5. Otherwiſe the Will of God is not the firſt in the order of cauſes, is capable of motives from without, both which are clearly againſt the perfection of the Divine Nature, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe God is not ſo perfectly happy, but there is a happineſſe imaginable beyond his happineſſe: It is greater happineſſe that all things whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be fully according to his Will, then that any thing be beſide it; and therefore foraſmuch as God is perfectly happy to the greateſt perfection imaginable, it muſt needs be his Will that thoſe things ſhould be, which yet he approves not as good, but approves as good, that they though not good, but evill, be.</p>
               <p>Another Objection yet againſt this abſolute power in God: Did God make man to damne him, and to this end decree that he ſhould ſin?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Scripture doth not much abhorre from ſuch like expreſſions, <hi>He made the wicked for the day of evill, veſſells of wrath fitted for deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.</hi> but not according to the meaning of this Objection doth it uſe them, which holds forth thus much, as if the torments of periſhing ſinners ſhould be the <hi>Terminus acquieſcentiae</hi> in the breaſt of God, that wherein he reſts, as wherein he hath obtained his end, as willing their condemnation for it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>God wills the condemnation of the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58707:26"/>from himſelfe, and for himſelfe, not for it ſelfe; for it ſelfe, he neither wills the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Reprobate, nor the ſalvation of the Elect, but he wills all things, and hath made all things that are made for his owne glory; therefore he hath not made man either to damne him, or to ſave him, in that ſenſe, but having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to glorifie on the one hand his mercy tempered with his juſtice; on the other, his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging juſtice in mans finall condition, he muſt needs determine thereupon, as the entire meanes without which that end could not be brought to paſſe, both to make man, and to permit him to linne, and to recover ſome from ſinne, and ſave them, to harden others in ſinne, and condemne them; ſo that the condemnation of the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate is not the end of Gods decree, but part of that meanes whereby the end, the glory of his revenging juſtice is accompliſh't; therefore when it is ſaid, he made the wicked for the day of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, it is ſaid withall, he made all things for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, veſſells of wrath fitted for deſtruction, withall that he might ſhew forth his wrath, and make his power knowne. And now we are come to the ſecond part of the Apoſtles anſwer, where he expoſtulates firſt, the ſupreme end: 2. The righteous execution of Gods decree.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The ſupreme ends: What if God willing to ſhew forth his wrath, and make his power known, v. 22. and that he might make known the riches of his glory, &amp;c.? v. 23.</p>
               <p>We have have ſeen formerly that which occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the Objection, v. 19. muſt needs be the decree of God, in that it ariſeth above the fall and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of man: To this therefore the Apoſtle hath
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58707:26"/>reſpect; Which, firſt, he juſtifies by the ends God propounded to himſelfe, The glorifying his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and mercy. The glory of God is the end of all, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36. as all things from him, ſo all things to him; and as God is to be glorified of all, ſo is he all manner of wayes to be glorified, in all his Attributes diſplayed, his Wiſdome, Power, Holineſſe, Mercy, Juſtice, &amp;c. this is by Divines called the good of the Univerſe, by Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe underſtanding all things created as one en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire frame, ſo making (as it were) a clear Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Glaſſe, wherein the Majeſty of God ſhines forth, the good of the Univerſe that reſplenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and luſtre of the Divine Majeſty, in the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of his perfections in all things: The wiſdom of God therefore dictating this way for the glory of his Mercy and Juſtice, (thoſe attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes into the glory whereof all the works of his hands are finally reſolved) God is hereby ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in his decree; and indeed this is the onely Juſtice which can have place in the decrees of God, that he decree nothing but what is beſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own wiſdom for his own glory, <hi>(Juſtitia condecentiae)</hi> and therefore the propoſal of ſuch an end as his wiſdome ſuggeſts to be for his glory, doth alone juſtifie God. Yet ſo doth he decree to glorifie his Juſtice, as withall his Power, or his dominion over his creature, which referrs ſtill to the liberty of his decree; ſo that whereas it is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that they are veſſells of wrath fitted for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, this hath reſpect to Gods intention, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining them to be ſuch as the Potter makes at his pleaſure his veſſels, ſome for honor, others for diſhonor; in vaine is that objection, that they are fitted of themſelves, which is ſo far true that they
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58707:27"/>corrupt themſelves, and are ſo fitted for condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but withall here is reference to Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, becauſe his power or dominion is thus ſhewn over man to be created, as the Potters over his clay, according to <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The righteous execution, God condemns not till they have ſinned, nay, he indures them ſinning againſt him with much long-ſuffering, nay, we may adde that which other Texts of Scripture hold forth, he condemns none, but withall they condemn themſelves, in the midſt of all their que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioning the juſtice of God, and cavilling againſt it, their owne conſcience gives teſtimony to the righteouſneſſe of God in condemning them. Here then we are to diſtinguiſh betwixt the decree and the execution of it; In the decree the Soveraignty, and therein the liberty of God hath place, and only that righteouſneſs whereby he is juſt to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in being true to his own glory; In the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his decree, his righteouſneſs towards his creature hath place, in his decree he is not moved by any reſpect of ſin, in the execution of his decree he puniſheth not but for ſin; his decree therefore is ſo abſolute as withall regular: abſolute in it ſelfe, regular for execution, as above ſin, and all reſpects of ſin, ſo much as fore-ſeen as a motive to his will: So it is his will that for ſin, and for ſin onely ſhall the reprobate be condemned, and the end of his decree being the glory of his uſtice, he can no other way condemn then for ſin.</p>
               <p>Thus have we ſeen the Apoſtles diſcourſe of this great Myſtery, which being opened we ſhall be the clearer and briefer in the reſt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:58707:27"/>
            <head>THE THIRD SERMON:</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 11.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But the Election hath obtained it, and the reſt were hardned.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E ſhall now proceed to confirme the Doctrine:</p>
            <p n="1">1. For that part of it which ſpeaks to Election.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the other of Reprobation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For Election let us thus deſcribe it.</p>
            <p>It is the eternall decree of God whereby he hath of meer love and good pleaſure, ordained effectually to eternall life, and all bleſſings making for life in Chriſt, a certaine number and thoſe the feweſt of men, to the praiſe of his glorious grace.</p>
            <p>In this deſcription we have theſe particulars to obſerve.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Election is the decree or purpoſe of God.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:58707:28"/>
2. That it is his eternall decree.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That it is for eternall life.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That it is of perſons, and that a certain and determined number ſingled out by name.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That it is of the feweſt of men.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That it is of love and good pleaſure.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Of meer love and arbitrary pleaſure above all reſpects in man.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That it is as for eternall life, ſo for all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings making for life in Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That it is effectuall hereunto.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That it is to the praiſe of the glorious grace of God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is his purpoſe or decree, two words the Scripture here uſeth. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> purpoſe, <hi>Scilicet.</hi> a ſetting down before hand, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. his purpoſe, and the counſel of his will, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.11. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purpoſe, tranſlated Predeſtination; it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports to ordain before hand, ſuch as within cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain bounds and limits are to receive what others without thoſe bounds ſhall not partake of, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29. the eternall diſtinction and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration betwixt man and man, for their finall ſtate having here its firſt riſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is his eternall degree; If his decree, an immanent act in the breaſt of God, it muſt be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall; nothing is new in God, though all things be new from him: if this diſcourſe ſhall not be ſo clear to ſome, Scripture teſtimonie is clear, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.4. Choſen us before the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world, ſo the Kingdom prepared for them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34. and the redeemer to bring them to that Kingdom,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>The word tranſlated fore-ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.20. <hi>Whence it is clear that fore-know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Scripture language is not a meere preſcience, but points out the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God; for who can think that God fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw in the humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Chriſt any thing ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent to his decree, whereby he was moved to unite it perſonally to the Son; ſo as in the divine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Son ſhould ſubſiſt?</hi>
               </note> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is for eternall life, <hi>Stapleton</hi> the Jeſuite
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58707:28"/>(and he hath others even amongſt our ſelves to follow him) would put off what the Apoſtle hath about Election, <hi>Rom</hi> 9. as though what is there ſpoken, aimed at the inheritance of the Land of <hi>Conaan,</hi> the birth-right &amp;c. and not at eternall life, and they will have it, that what the Apoſtle there ſpake of Gods love to <hi>Jacob,</hi> and hatred of <hi>Eſau,</hi> concerned <hi>Jacob</hi> and all his ſeed in common, and <hi>Eſau</hi> and all his: and therefore to reach no further then the inheritance of <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> for <hi>Jacob</hi> and his ſeed, and the deſtruction of <hi>Eſau's</hi> inheritance, as expreſt by <hi>Malachi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that it is for eternall life, is very clear. 1. In the 9th. to the <hi>Romans</hi> by divers Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the Objection which was about the Jews refuſing the Goſpell, and ſo miſſing of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life; the Apoſtle in his wiſh, inſinuating clearly as much, and in the following anſwer diſputing upon that ſuppoſition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle makes the diſtinction, which he derives from Election and Reprobation in <hi>Jacobs</hi> own ſeed, v 6. which he backs with the like diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in <hi>Abrahams</hi> and <hi>Iſaac's</hi> Family; then deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all from Gods different decree, gives <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> ſpeciall inſtances thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Apoſtle inſtanceth for Reprobation in <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> wherein if any man ſhall think he aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not at eternall condemnation, which yet the Teſtimony of his hardning may evince, his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing diſcourſe will conclude it, and clearly determine this controverſie; and therefore,</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Apoſtle concludes the Reprobate Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of wrath fitted for deſtruction; and the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Veſſels of Mercy, fitted for glory.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:58707:29"/>
5. What he ſpeakes of Veſſels of mercy fitted for glory, he applies to the called of the Gentiles, as well as of the Jews: and can any man now poſſibly perſwade himſelf that this is meant on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or mainly of outward priviledges? as thus in the 9th, ſo in the 11th. Chap. where the Apoſtle reſumes the ſame Objection, and anſwers it in the ſame manner, diſtinguiſhing betwixt the Elect and the reſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He oppoſeth the Elects obtaining to the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the reſt, and doth not hardening with the following Teſtimonies againſt them, verſ. 7.8, 9, 10. relate to eternall wrath: then muſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection alſo relate to eternall glory. Further, what the hardned Jews, through their fall miſſe of; the called Gentiles, together with the Elect Jews obtain; and what is that? Not the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> outward birth-right, or any ſuch outward priviledge &amp;c. but Goſpell-ſalvation, verſ. 11. Reconciliation, verſ. 15. and is not the ſurrogation of the Gentiles, the planting of them into the Covenant of life? Many accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to outward adminiſtration, the Elect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, by effectuall vocation: Again, what ſhall be the main of their reſtoring, verſ. 25.26. onely outward priviledges? Nay but that ſtate of ſalvation by embracing the Goſpell which the Gentiles now are in, the Gentiles ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe herein depending upon the Jews return. And as theſe Scriptures wherein this controverſie is expreſly handled, are clear; ſo for other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29.30. there is the chain of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life; whereas Election is the firſt linke, ſo glory is the laſt: the intermediate, all ſuch as tend to glory; as here the Chain, ſo otherwhere the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58707:29"/>Book of eternall life, <hi>Reu.</hi> 13.8. and 17.8. and 20.12.15. and 3 5. and <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.3. Objection, that 3 <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. ſuppoſeth Election changeable, that their names who are enrolled may be blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The unchangeableneſs of Election will hereafter be fully cleared; in the mean time to prevent miſtake, this is ſpoken after the manner of men, and ſutable to the metaphor, to blot out of the book of life, is no more but to deny it to him, or not to plead eternall life on his behalf; and ſo make manifeſt, that though his name ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be written in that book; yet it never was a like inſtance which muſt receive this interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we have Mat. 13.12. Concerning the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Goſpel Myſtery. Whoſoever hath not, from him ſhall be taken, that which he hath, that is, that which he ſeemed to have, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.18. But if he but ſeemed to have it, and had it not, how can it be taken from him? onely thus, it ſhall be made manifeſt that he did but ſeem to have it, but had it not in truth: But to return, Election is called the book of Life; therefore it is for eternall life; agreeable hereunto the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect are likewiſe ſaid to have their names written in heaven; add to this that which is clear in the Scripture, that the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the birth-right &amp;c. were outward pledges of the eternal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.9.10. and the Apoſtlesdiſcourſe of <hi>Eſau's</hi> ſubjection to <hi>Jacob, Rom.</hi> 9. ſetting forth therein the difference of their ſpicituall ſtate in order to eternall life, as we have now ſeen in ſhewing the Apoſtles Doctrine of Election and Reprobation, there to reach to eternall life, and death clearly conclude as much, a pledge of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau's</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:58707:30"/>ſpirituall ſervitude, according to the mind of the Oracle, we have in the loſſe of the birth-right prophanely deſpiſed by him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.32. &amp;c. 4. That it is of perſons; and that a ſet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and determined number ſingled out by name in the counſell of God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The diſourſe of the Apoſtle, Rom. 9.11. clearly holds forth this, the ſum whereof is, that whereas the greateſt part of the Jews refuſed the Goſpell to their own condemnation, a remnant embraced it unto ſalvation; the ſupream ground of this difference was the different decree of God, loving ſome in order to eternall life, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting others in order to eternall death, of which <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> are ſingular inſtances; and by vertue of this different decree, ſome are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and carryed on to the enjoyment of life; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hardned unto death, agreeable to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Election, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.29.30. The purpoſe of God pitcheth upon ſome for life in the firſt place, whence he adminiſters the whole method of life to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is manifeſt by that metaphor, whereby ſo frequently Election is expreſt, <hi>viz.</hi> The book of Life; It is not a Statute book, ſetting down the Lawes, or the way of Life; but a Regiſter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are enrolled the Heirs of Life.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The following particulars concluding it, every one apart together joyntly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That is of the feweſt of men, if it be not of perſons, but of the way of life; thus as ſome would have it, (beleevers ſhall be ſaved, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers ſhall be damned, not determining who ſhall believe and be ſaved, who ſhall not beleeve and be damned;) then is it not either of the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58707:30"/>feweſt or of the moſt, but either of all alike, or of none alike.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is of love and good pleaſure.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Of meere love and arbitrary pleaſure; love muſt needs relate to perſons: So in the inſtance (<hi>Jacob</hi> have I loved) meer love and arbitrary plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure muſt ariſe above all different reſpects, either exiſtent or foreſeen in men: now there is no place for this love, in caſe it be not of perſons, but onely a decree ſetting down upon what terms and in what way men ſhall ſaved.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That it is as for eternall life, ſo for all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings tending thereto; for if the faith and holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe that are ſaved, and all other graces and priviledges depend upon this decree, and are the fruits of it; then it muſt needs be, that this decree firſt pitcheth upon the perſons, before they be conſidered as beleeving and holy; and becauſe God hath ſet them apart in love, as upon whom he will glorifie his grace, therefore he gives thoſe graces and priviledges to them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That it is effectuall to eternall life; for then is not the decree ſuſpended upon mans obeying the call of God, and perſevering therein, but by vertue of this decree, he doth effectually obey, and perſevere.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Herein is the glory of divine grace, that he makes Veſſels of honour (finds them not ſuch) having afore prepared them (in his eternal coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel) unto glory; It remaines therefore that we prove theſe particulars, which do at once both confirm the former, and further open this great Myſtery of Election: Therefore 5. It is of the feweſt of men; Here is one particular that mans reaſon is not willing to hear of, but for this, the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58707:31"/>Scripture is expreſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.16. Firſt, If we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thoſe who are outwardly called, with thoſe who are not, we ſhall find the feweſt called; for about the firſt 4000 years, how was the world generally overlooked in point of out ward call, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.30. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, God was then plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo to overlook the Children of men, as not to declare his will to them, or call upon them to repent by his word or voice; for ſeverall ages, ſome ſpeciall families of <hi>Seth's</hi> line, of whom <hi>Noah:</hi> afterward one little Nation of the Jewes derived from <hi>Abraham, Pſal.</hi> 147.19. and 2 Since the times of the Goſpell, how many great Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (and even at this day) unto whom the word of God is not made known? but all the Elect are called; for thoſe of years generally by an outward call (and even their infants in their Church ſtate, and faederall intereſt have an outward call.) All of them inwardly ſo called as juſtified, and in concluſion glorified, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. Now that Gods Election raigns generally amongſt thoſe that are outwardly called for themſelves and their Children; it is clear enough, becauſe he hath appointed his word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the meanes of life; and generally where he hath choſen to the end, he hath likewiſe choſen to the meanes, otherwiſe the meanes would not be ſo choice and excellent bleſſings, ſo highly to be prized as the Scripture ſets them forth; if then generally the Elect be outwardly called, and amongſt ſuch as are called outwardly Salvation takes place, and theſe are the feweſt, then are the Elect the feweſt; but here is yet another ſtep, all the Elect are in time inwardly and effectually called, and onely who are in time ſo called, are
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58707:31"/>Elect before time; But of thoſe many that are called outwardly but a few thus, hence but a few ſaved, ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. a remnant according to Election.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is of love and good pleaſure, 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Love, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.13. with the 11. verſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, good pleaſure, Eph. 1.5. &amp; 9. this love expreſt in ſingling out, and fore appointing to life, of the ſame meaning <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. with 5, the people whom he fore-knew, the remnant according to Election; to know in Scripture phraſe importing to embrace in love, (after ye have known God, or rather are known of him, he knows <hi>(Scil.)</hi> he approves the way of the righteous, on the contrary to the wicked, I know you not,) ſo 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.2. and 20. ſo 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. there <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Lord knows (as thoſe whom he hath in ſpecial manner loved, and built upon the ſure foundation of life his own purpoſe) who are his. 2. It is his decree of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing love, love with choice ſo imbracing theſe as refuſing thoſe; this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Election holds forth, limiting his love and good pleaſure, for life to ſuch as he hath in his purpoſe gathered apart from others;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> what <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or rather praefinition is to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> purpoſe, the ſame is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Election to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; to love and good pleaſure.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is of meere love and abſolute pleaſure, not upon either good works, on faith fore-ſeen, this is clear. 1. From the 9th. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> verſ. 11. where the Apoſtle makes Election the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God, as of him that calleth, and for this end that it might abide: Now it is the effectuall call of God that gives faith, and in this call is
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58707:32"/>that renewing work of the holy Ghoſt, whereby the Elect are brought into the ſtate of life, and principled for good works in order to life; and this call of God is a ſure and unmovable founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of eternall life to the Elect, as borrowing nothing of man, but depending wholly upon the unchangeable purpoſe of him, in whom is no change, neither ſhadow of turning; foraſmuch then as in our call we receive faith, and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and Election is of God as of him that calls, he neither fore ſees faith nor good works in any after-called ones, antecedently to the decree of Election; but in his decree of giving them, it is that he fore-ſees them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe arguments uſed in the explication of the 11th. verſ. towards the latter end of the firſt Sermon, to prove this generall concluſion; That no purpoſe of God can depend upon any thing without himſelf, will here conclude.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That diſcourſe in the ſecond Sermon, from almoſt the beginning to the end of that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, proving that not onely comparative Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination is above all different reſpects in the Creature, but ſingle above all reſpects, and thence concluding that not man conſidered as fallen, but conſidered as not yet Created, muſt be the object of Predeſtination, will here likewiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This abſolute and arbitrary pleaſure of God is really and experimentally made manifeſt, in his diſpenſations to the Children of men, (why did he chuſe one Nation of the Jews to be the onely Nation of the Covenant; and therefore the people amongſt whom generally his ſecret Election raigned, over-looking all the Nations
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:58707:32"/>of the world beſide? did he fore-ſee indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently upon his decree, greater inclinableneſs to faith and holineſs in them, then in all the world beſide? I think no man will be willing to own ſo wild a conceit: I am ſure <hi>Moſes</hi> tels them the contrary, <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.4.5. why doth he ſend the Goſpell ſince the door of faith hath been opened to the Gentiles, to ſuch a people rather then to another? Is he not therein found of thoſe that ſought him not? why did he in ſuch an age firſt make known the myſtery of the Goſpell, to all Nations for the obedience of Faith, and ſo for life, by Jeſus Chriſt; which myſtery till that time was kept ſecret from the beginning of the world, Rom. 16.25.26? what is here to be ſaid? but even ſo O Father, becauſe ſo it ſeemed good in thine eyes.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is the Election of Grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.5. and therefore not of works, verſ. the 6. if Election, not of works, then not of works fore-ſeen; for Election being Gods eternall purpoſe, as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath been proved, and the Apoſtle in his whole diſcourſe, diſputes upon that as a granted prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, there could be no other way whereby it might be ſuppoſed of works, then of works fore-ſeen; if not of works fore-ſeen, then not of faith fore-ſeen, becauſe faith here puts on the nature of works, as being a qualification in our ſelves, commending us to God by that which hath prevented his free gift, Hence:</p>
            <p n="6">6. Upon the ſuppoſal of faith and works, or faith alone fore-ſeen, the Doctrine of free grace is wholly undermined in the foundation; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more frequent in Scripture, then that our Call is of grace, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. &amp; 9. Faith is the gift
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58707:33"/>of God, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.8. Grace alwaies ſo interpreted as to ſhut out works, to forbid glorifying, (yet matter of glorifying granted; if there be any thing in our ſelves before it be given of God to commend us to him;) Now to what end is all this, if we have prevented the free gift of God, even from all eternity, by fore-ſeen faith and works, engaging his purpoſe for us?</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is manifeſt in the inſtance of Chriſt, the head of the Elect, that God proceeds in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection according to his abſolute and arbitrary pleaſure; what reaſon can be given, other then meerly the abſolute will and good pleaſure of God, that the man Chriſt, conceived of the God of <hi>David;</hi> a mortall man, ſhould in the wombe be made the head of the Angels, the onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son of God, the image and glory of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the light, righteouſneſs, and life of the world? Can any man make himſelf believe there could be any thing foreſeen in the humane nature of Chriſt, to move the Lord thus to purpoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him? In the Churches head ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> we have a moſt clear evidence of moſt free Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that it is thus of meer love and arbitrary pleaſure, not of faith or works fore-ſeen, is yet further manifeſt by the next main particular.</p>
            <p n="8">8. God in his purpoſe of Election decrees as life, ſo all ſpirituall bleſſings making for life, to be freely given us in Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29.30. there the whole method of ſalvation is derived from Election, <hi>Ethe.</hi> 1.3.4.5. we are bleſſed with all ſpiritual bleſſings according to Election the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all; and of the giving of Chriſt in whom we receive all, thence our holineſſe verſ 4. our adoption verſ. 5. our redemption, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58707:33"/>of our ſins, verſ. 7. the diſcovery of the Goſpel myſtery, verſ. 9. our title to eternall life, verſ. 11. the word there uſed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, we are taken by lot, or have our lot aſſigned us, further hinting to us, how little the will of man hath here to doe.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>We are Elected in Chriſt, but we are no otherwiſe in Chriſt then by faith</hi> (Ergo) <hi>our faith fore-ſeen is the cauſe of our Election.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. We ſhall give the true meaning; we are Elected in Chriſt, that is, we are Elected to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in him united to him as the members to the head, all bleſſings prepared for us in our Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Chriſt is not the motive of Gods decree, but the meanes of accompliſhing it: Thus the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. and 9. 2. We ſhall confirm it, that it muſt be ſo underſtood.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſt himſelf is ordained the mediatour of the new Covenant by vertue of Election, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16. The Apoſtle there ſhewes that God in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving the Covenant of grace, whereby Chriſt is the head and mediatour, had a ſpeciall eye to the Elect ſeed; that ſeed to whom, to all whom the Covenant ſhall be ſure for life. Chriſt was not then the motive to Gods decree, but for their ſakes to whom he had drereed life, did he ordain Chriſt a mediatour, and in his hand the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Faith whereby we might be conceived to be repreſented to the decreeing eye of God as in Chriſt, is given us by vertue of Election, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no otherwiſe fore-ſeen in us then in that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, whereby God hath determined to give it us, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. <hi>John</hi> 10. verſ. 26.27. becauſe they are Chriſts ſheep, they hear his voice and believe,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58707:34"/>in their effectuall Call; therefore his ſheep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their call; that is according to Election, whence it proceeds originally that they hear and obey his Call: Hence <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1. The faith of Gods Elect; as faith, ſo holineſs, or whatſoever might be imagined to commend us to God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. All depending upon faith, therefore if faith be not praevious to the decree, neither is holineſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We have ſeen before our holineſs depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Predeſtination thereto.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Otherwiſe we rather chuſe God in Chriſt, then God us, <hi>John</hi> 15.16.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Then were Election of works contrary ſo expreſly to <hi>Rom.</hi> 9 11. Hence we learn the true meaning of thoſe Texts of Scripture, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. and 13. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. in both which it is ſaid, we are choſen in ſanctification of the ſpirit (for ſo it is in the Originall) &amp;c. that is, we are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen that by the ſanctification of the ſpirit, &amp;c. (to which ſanctification we are likewiſe choſen) we might obtain glory: from this particular then thus concluded it is further manifeſt, both that Election is of perſons, and that it is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute.</p>
            <p n="9">9. As it is for life, and all bleſſings making for life; ſo it is effectual unto life, not one, nor other of Gods Elect ſhall ever finally miſcarry, but as only they, ſo every one of them ſhall moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have life.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The purpoſe of Election is firm, unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, irrevocable, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11. that it may abide, therefore hath it ſo unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a foundation, the will of God alone, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The immutability of his counſell, that which can never be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58707:34"/>placed as the word imports.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By vertue of Election, they are moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly preſerved againſt all temptations, that though in themſelves before their call they be children of wrath for their preſent ſtate, after their call through weakneſs and remaining cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, they might a thouſand times miſ-car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: yet by vertue of Gods unchangeable Election. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. They ſhall every one of them in due time be called effectually. 2. They ſhall be upheld af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their call againſt all temptations, and ſurely brought to glory.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they ſhall be every one of them ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually called, beſides what is clearly confirmed by thoſe Scriptures which were brought to prove the eighth particular; we ſhall add a further teſtimony or two, <hi>John</hi> 37.38.39, 40. where we may obſerve; 1. That it is from the gift of the Father originally, that we are delivered unto the care and cuſtody of Chriſt; we are the Fathers by Election, before we be Chriſts by redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therefore not choſen becauſe fore-ſeen as redeemed by Chriſt, and applying by faith his redemption; but becauſe choſen, therefore gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into the hands of Chriſt, that by him we might be redeemed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That every one of the Elect as they are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the Father, ſo they ſhall certainly come to Chriſt; there is their effectuall Call; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall they have a power to come, but actually they ſhall come.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That every one of them thus comming ſhall certainly have life; all this verſ. 37. which is further confirmed, 38.39.40. So in the 44. and 45. verſes, there are theſe concluſions.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:58707:35"/>
1. No man can come to Chriſt, but he that is drawn of the Father.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whoſoever is drawn comes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whoſoever being drawn comes, ſhall have eternall life; theſe in the 44. verſe, the promiſe in the latter end of the verſe (I will raiſe him up at the laſt day) neceſſarily ſuppoſing that he that is drawn comes, which is further confirmed and cleared in the 45. verſ. where the drawing of the Father is interpreted his teaching, where two things are affirmed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they ſhall all <hi>(viz)</hi> all that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath given to Chriſt, be taught of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This teaching of his is ſuch an heart-tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, that every man that hath been thus taught of the Father comes: Hence it is manifeſt;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Elect have an effectual, and therefore a peculiar teaching of the Father, there is not one common aide to all, upon which they are left to difference themſelves who have received it; whoſoever partakes in this teaching he doth come, all come not, therefore all have not been thus taught; hence St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> If every one which hath been taught comes, then muſt it needs be, that he that comes not, hath not been taught: Again,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. de. predeſt. ſanct. c.</hi> 8.</note> what is that? Every one that hath heard and learned of the Father comes to me; but this, there is none which heares and learnes of the Father but he comes to me; for if every one which hath heard of the Father and learned, comes cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly; whoſoever comes not, hath not heard of the Father and learned; for had he heard and learned, he had come.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That as they are by divine teachings effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally cal'd, ſo they do finally perſevere, and every
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58707:35"/>one of them obtain life, they are ſo drawn of the Father and ſo taught by him, as they are raiſed up at the laſt laſt day, and that unto glory as is manifeſt, in that this raiſing is a fruit of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers drawing to Chriſt, and by comparing verſ. 44. with 39. and 40.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is here further manifeſt, that onely the Elect to whom it is given to come, have the power to come to Chriſt, whoſoever comes not, have not the power of comming.</p>
            <q>No man can come except he be drawn of the Father, be that is drawn doth come; whence the diſcourſe lies clear, all that are drawn come, all that have power are drawn; therefore all that have power come, but all come not, therefore all have not power, onely the Elect <hi>(viz.)</hi> thoſe that are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the Father to Chriſt come, therefore they onely have the power of comming.</q>
            <p>As for the Objection, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.12. it is too light, they would argue thence that ſome given of the Father to Chriſt, according to Election may pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is contrary to verſ. 2. of this 17. Chapter, and to <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.37. &amp;c. as formerly we have ſeen.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The form of ſpeech there uſed, will not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer neceſſarily that he was given of the Father; ſometimes ſuch a form of ſpeech is uſed in ſound exceptive from the propoſition foregoing, but in the true meaning excluſive of it, ſo <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.4. It was not lawfull for <hi>David</hi> and thoſe that were with him, except (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) onely the Prieſts to eat the Shew-bread, this ſounds as though ſome of <hi>Davids</hi> company were Prieſts; the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58707:36"/>is, it was not lawful for any of them in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary caſe, becauſe there were no Prieſts to eat of that bread; ſo here, none that the Father hath given to Chriſt ſhal periſh, except <hi>Judas</hi> the ſon of perdition: The meaning according to the former inſtance may very wel be, that whereas the other Apoſtles becauſe given of the Father ſhal ſurely be kept to eternal life, <hi>Judas</hi> as not being one of thoſe that were ſo given, is a loſt man.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Grant him given of the Father, yet is it to be underſtood of another giving, then that which is according to eternall Election.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He is given in regard of outward ſtate, as all are that are outwardly called, and make profeſſion of Chriſt, though few of thoſe bee choſen.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In regard of Apoſtolical Function, in which ſenſe he is ſaid likewiſe to be choſen, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.70. but for that giving, wherein is laid the foundation of eternal life formerly ſpoken of, had he been ſo given to Chriſt, he had never departed from him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.2.19. and when Chriſt ſpeakes of that Election he expreſly ſhuts out <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, Joh.</hi> 13.18.</p>
            <p>Hitherto that all the Elect ſhal in time be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually called.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They ſhall be upheld after their cal againſt all temptations, ſo as they ſhal certainly perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in the grace of their cal unto eternal life: Theſe Scriptures which prove their cal, do like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe confirme their certaine obtaining of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, as we have ſeen in the opening them; add to them 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.24. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.8. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.8. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.15. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:58707:36"/>34. &amp;c. All which Scriptures clearly ſhew that the ſure foundation of life and perſeverance in grace received unto life is laid in Election, ſo as not any one of Gods Elect ſhal ever fal ſhort of life; it was with ſpecial eye to the Elect that the Covenant of Grace was ordained, and ſo contrived, that by that Covenant life might be ſure to them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16.</p>
            <p>Before we paſs to the tenth and laſt particular, from the Doctrine of Election hitherto opened, we may take notice of two or three miſ-ſhapen Monſters nouriſhed in the Arminian Doctrine.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The uncertainty of called mans ſpiritual and finall condition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The uncertainty, or rather impoſſibility of Gods fore-knowledge thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Temporary Election and Reprobation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the firſt: It being inconſiſtent with the liberty of mans wil, (according to their Doctrine,) that God ſhould in the cal of a ſinner determine his wil by the work of the holy Ghoſt, ſo as that it cannot come to paſſe but the ſinner ſhal obey his cal: And for perſeverance in the grace of his cal, the liberty of mans wil requires (ſay they) that when God hath done all that he doth for any, yet may man for the iſſue not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere. Hence it muſt needs follow, that all is at meere peradventure, whether any one of all the ſonnes and daughters of men ſhould be ſaved or not? whether ever there ſhould have been any Militant Church upon earth, or Triumphant in heaven, or not? whether Chriſt ſhould haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken our nature upon him; his offices, have done and ſuffered all in vain, or not?</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the ſecond: For as much as mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58707:37"/>both for grace here, and glory hereafter, depends upon the uſe of his wil, imbracing or reſiſting the cal of God, continuing in, or falling from the grace received in his cal, and they wil not allow that God ſhal by his decree particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determine how this or that man ſhal uſe his wil, and they require it as eſſential to the liberty of mans wil, that he may as to the event, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace or refuſe the motions of Gods Spirit, whether in his call, or after it; how can it bee that what is no way certaine to be, as having no certain foundation neither in God nor man, can be certainly fore-known, the certain fore-know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of that which is no way certaine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, involving a contradiction? Hence they are wont to decline this argument of Gods fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, and ſometimes ſome of them ſpare not to deny it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For the third: Hence it muſt follow, that the Election of any perſon cannot be till the laſt moment of life; the reprobation of any perſon not til the time of obſtinacy in ſinne; for they make faith and final perſeverance therein, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to election; unbelief and obſtinacy in ſinne ſubſtrate to reprobation: Now this muſt be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther actual, or in the fore-knowledge of God, but in the fore-knowledge of God it cannot be, according to their Doctrine, as we but now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; therefore it muſt be actual, and ſo election and reprobation not eternal, but in time; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no decrees or imminent acts of God. Hence they ſpeake ſometimes not much incongruouſly to this reſult of their Doctrine; <hi>Arminius</hi> tels us of an external act of reprobation, and wee hear from his followers, and thoſe of greateſt
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58707:37"/>note, that Election is not confirmed from ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting; that it is revocable, that men ſometimes of elect become reprobate, and of reprobate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, &amp;c. What portents of opinion theſe are, even
<q>
                  <l>Qualia credibile eſt rictu ruct aſſe trifauci</l>
                  <l>Cerberon &amp; ſtygii monſtra tremenda lacus.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The former Doctrine with cleare evidence of Scripture, truth hath already manifeſted, to the praiſe of his glorious grace, or to the praiſe of the glory of his grace, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.6.</p>
            <p>There are foure things in the decree of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, making much for the glory of his grace.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is to ſuch great bleſſings in Chriſt, the greateſt of bleſſings, and the foundation of the reſt; <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5. 6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is ſo effectuall thereunto, as in the building of the Temple at ſetting up the top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone there was loud acclamations of grace, <hi>Zach.</hi> 4. ſo here in the accompliſhment of all bleſſings prepared in Election, when God ſhall be admired to all eternity in thoſe that believe, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. in his decree of Election, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of faith and all bleſſings conſequent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on faith, ſhal this admiration ultimately fix.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That it is ſo free in oppoſition to all works and faith in man, it being and abiding wholly of him that calls not believers, but unto faith, nor the holy, but to holineſſe, as formerly hath been declared.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That it is peculiar, it ſo imbraceth ſome, as refuſeth others, that it is accompanied with the decree of Reprobation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.22, 23. there is
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58707:38"/>nothing more raviſhing the heart of a believer, whether here or in heaven, then this conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Why did God ſet his love upon me, and chuſe me unto life, refuſing ſo many others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They that pretended much to the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of free-grace, are for vniverſal grace, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal redemption, and ſuch an election (or no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection rather) as may ſtand therewith, betray no little ignorance (how wiſe ſoever they ſeem in their own eyes) of the grace of God indeed, and the true arguments of his glory ariſing from his grace.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:58707:38"/>
            <head>THE FOURTH SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 11.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But the reſt were hardned.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E now come to the Decree of Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the word, oppoſite to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 41.9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the thing, it may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered partly from the precedent Doctrine of Election, partly from expreſſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture concerning it.</p>
            <p>It is the eternal decree of God, whereby hee hath, meerly becauſe he would, hated the reſt of men, (the ſame is true of the Angells, but wee confine our diſcourſe to man) beſides his Elect, ſo as to appoint them to diſhonour and deſtruction for ever by ſinne, for the glory partly of his ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne power over man, partly of his revenging juſtice upon periſhing ſinners, and laſtly of the riches of his mercy upon his choſen and ſaved ones.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:58707:39"/>
This deſcription wil be clearly made good in the particulars of it, by looking backe into the former diſcourſe, that we ſhal not need to be long upon it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there is in God a decree oppoſite to the eternal decree of Election, is manifeſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11. as hath by a threefold argument been proved, in opening that Verſe in the firſt Sermon, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by opening the 14, 15, 16, 17, 18. Verſes at the beginning of the ſecond Sermon, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Obſervation upon them. (I muſt here, and divers times hereafter in this diſcourſe of Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, refer the Reader to what hath been ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in opening the ninth to the <hi>Romans,</hi> &amp;c. both becauſe repetitions of the ſame thing would needleſly increaſe the bulke of this diſcourſe, and breed confuſion in the underſtanding.)</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is his decree of hatred, this hatred oppoſed to electing love is manifeſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.13. that it is ſuch an hatred, as refers to the excluſion out of the Covenant of life, and to eternal death, is there proved in handling the third inſtance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Ver. 10, 11, 12, 13. joyntly in the firſt Sermon, as likewiſe in the third Sermon almoſt at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, in handling the third particular, that Election is for eternal life: The proofe thereof carrying along with it the proofe of this too, that Reprobation is for eternal death. But for our more diſtinct apprehenſion, we have here three things to conſider.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Wherein this hatred conſiſts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Who are the objects of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What is the ground of it.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, it conſiſts in two things: 1. The decree of permitting ſin, in order to hardning
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58707:39"/>in it: 2. The decree of hardning in ſinne, in order to condemnation for it; or rather in the decree of God for two things. Firſt, for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of ſin, in order to hardning in it: And ſecondly, for hardning in ſin, in order to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation for it.</p>
            <p>That God decrees the being of ſinne in the world, hath been proved by divers arguments towards the end of the ſecond Sermon, and that it be by his permiſſion, without which it could not be. Now further, for the Reprobate he decrees the permitting of it in order to hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and their hardning in it in order to their condemnation: Hence the method whereby the Reprobates are carryed on to condemnation, which is according to the decree of God oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to Election, is by hardning, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18. (He will have mercy on whom he will have mercy) looking back-wards to his love of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and fore-ward to the honour, verſ. 21. and glory, 23. of the veſſels of mercy prepared thereunto, as thoſe on whom he would make known the riches of his glory. (And whom he wills he hardens) looking back-wards likewiſe to his hatred of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and for-ward to the diſhonour of (v. 21.) his wrath and power againſt, v. 22. the veſſels of wrath fitted for deſtruction, which by abuſing the long-ſuffering of God towards them, they in the end incur, ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.7. <hi>The Election hath obtained it, the reſt were hardned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By divine permiſſion, then to fall into ſin is common to the Elect with the Reprobate, and that both in <hi>Adam</hi> and themſelves, but with dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent aime on Gods part, and different fruit or
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58707:40"/>iſſue on mans, by the ſins of the Elect, way is made for their Redemption by Chriſt; by the ſins of the Reprobate, way is made for their fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall hardning in ſin, and ſo for eternall death, that as the love of God to the Elect is expreſt, 1. In their effectuall call. 2. In their finall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance; ſo his hatred to the Reprobate, 1. In leaving them to their ſins 2. In final hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in ſin. For further clearing this point in hand, let us reſolve one queſtion.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is it to harden in ſin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is the exerciſe of righteous judgement by God upon ſinners, whereby he gives them over ſo fully to the power of their own luſt, and to the dominion of Satan, that they are no longer capable of ſpirituall good, but on the contrary, not onely by all temptations to ſin, but by the moſt powerfull meanes againſt ſinne they ſhall grow worſe and worſe.</p>
            <p>We read of a two-fold hardning, one befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Diſciples of Chriſt; <hi>Mark</hi> 6 52. this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth it ſelf in ſottiſhneſs, oppoſite to due ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they underſtand not, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the loaves, the other peculiar to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, expreſſing it ſelf in ſtubbornneſs, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to due ſubmiſſion; thus <hi>Pharoah</hi> as, yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteſt thou thy ſelf againſt me? <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.17. It is this that we here ſpeak unto.</p>
            <p>Concerning this three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is the ſtate of a ſinner thus hardned? It is this, he is no longer capable of ſpirituall good, &amp;c. So with <hi>Pharoah,</hi> when the Apoſtle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanceth as an example of Reprobation, he ſtill grew worſe and worſe by all the great works of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:58707:40"/>God before him, and upon him, after every new plague, his heart hardned anew, <hi>Exod,</hi> 7.2.3.4. when the Magicians were forced to confeſs the power of God againſt them; ſtill his heart hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.19. ſo the Reprobate Jews, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.9.10. with <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. v. 14.15. their hardneſs of heart went on againſt all that they heard and ſaw in the word and workes of God by the Prophet, by Chriſt himſelf, and his Apoſtles, ſottiſhneſs and ſtubbornneſs, both prevailing in them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What is Gods way of hardning the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate? he gives them over ſo fully, &amp;c. as it is in the deſcription; here are two particulars eſpecially to be taken notice of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He gives them over fully to the power of their luſts, and this he doth by with-holding thoſe works of his ſpirit, for enlightning, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing, awing, enclining, which formerly he afforded: There is a time when even the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates (many of them) are in regard of meanes offorded, and the workes of Gods ſpirit upon them, by the means in a faire way for life, but they abuſing that light and thoſe motions of the ſpirit,; the Lord with-holds thoſe works of his, no longer reſtraining them as formerly, but ſuffering them to run headlong into all wickedneſſe wholly byaſſed by their luſts; hence God is ſaid to harden them, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 12.40 refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to that of <hi>Eſay</hi> 6.9, 10. he thus giving them over, and they are ſaid to harden them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.15. (their eyes have they clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, conmpare the Context) they given over increaſing in ſtubbornneſs againſt the Lord, ſo
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58707:41"/>in the Hiſtory of <hi>Pharoah;</hi> ſometimes God is ſaid to harden his heart, ſometimes he is ſaid to harden his own heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He gives them over to the dominion of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan (whom they have choſen rather to ſerve then God) as the inſtrument of his wrath, to blind them more, to ſmite them with further hardnes of heart, to infuſe into them, and ſtir up in them more enmity againſt God, thus 2 Theſ. 2.10, 11.12. God gives over ſuch as received not the love of the truth, &amp;c. to the effectuall deluſions of Satan, with certain aime at their damnation, thus 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.14. and 18.10. and 19.9. there is an evill ſpirit from the Lord ſtirring up <hi>Saul</hi> to rage and murder, an evill ſpirit, therefore the Devil, from the Lord, therefore he had commiſſion from God (as the lying ſpirit in the mouths of <hi>Ahabs</hi> Prophets had) and <hi>Saul</hi> was given up of God, to the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall working and dominion of that evill ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Lord as the ſupream mover acts them thus deſtitute of his grace, and wrought upon by Satan; hence the Lord is ſaid to harden, to fatten, to ſtrengthen, to turn the heart of the Reprobate unto evill; ſo for turning their hearts, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 105.25. (of the work of God upon the wills of men, moving them when they move ſinfully, he himſelf free from their ſinne, ſee more fully in anſwer to the firſt Objection in the laſt Sermon.)</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ground of this hardning work, it is their former ſinnes; therefore we ſay it is the exerciſe of the Lords righteous judgement up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58707:41"/>ſinners when he hardens, though the decree of permitting fin in order to hardning, and of hardning in order to condemnation, riſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſin either acted or foreſeen as that which ſhall be, the Lord in this decree of his ſeeing that it ſhall be as formerly hath been proved; yet the execution of this decree in hardning, ever followes ſin committed, ſo 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they received not the love of the truth, there was their ſin, God gave them up, &amp;c. there their judgement, ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.24.26. Thus have we ſeen wherein this hatred conſiſts, further clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to us, that ſuch a decree there is, and thus, and in this method do we underſtand that which is expreſt in the deſcription, that God appoints the Reprobate to diſhonour and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction for ever by ſin. Hence they are called veſſels for diſhonour and of wrath, fitted to deſtruction, <hi>Rom</hi> 9.21.22. Hence the Apoſtle tels us by clear inſinuation, that ſome are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wrath, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.9. ſpeaking of it as the great happineſſe of himſelf and the Saints there, that God had not appointed them to wrath, ſome he had appointed thereto, hence <hi>Iude</hi> 4. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain men fore-ordained, or fore-written to that judgement: as Election is the book of life, ſo Reprobation of death, the names of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate there Regiſtred for deſtruction, in vain it is objected that fore-writing there is nothing but <hi>Enochs</hi> fore-propheſying, verſ. 14. For</p>
            <p n="1">1. How doth it appear that <hi>Enochs</hi> Propheſie was written?</p>
            <p n="2">2. In that they in S. <hi>Judes</hi> time were by <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> propheſied of ſo many ages before, it is
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:58707:42"/>manifeſt they were ſo many ages before ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to judgement, &amp; if ſo many ages before, then from all eternity; there being no imaginable reaſon why in that age God ſhould firſt decree it, ſetting aſide that all the decrees of God are eternall, and that his love of Election, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of Reprobation are not at all of works done or fore-ſeen. Hence 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8. There are certain men appointed formerly, or put (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) to ſtumble at the Goſpell, diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient thereto, hence <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. the wicked are made for the day of evill; God in the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of man, hath the condemnation of the Reprobate for his own glory in his eye, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are they veſſels deſigned to diſhonour and deſtruction when the Lord formes them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.20, 21, 22. Hitherto that there is ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of hatred in God concerning the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, and wherein it conſiſts. Now</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the Object of this hatred, who are theſe Reprobates here ſpoken of?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> All but the Elect.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Election hath obtained (ſaith the Apoſtle) but the reſt were hardned, ſpeaking of the Jews; but in his following diſcourſe he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides the whole world into theſe two ranks, as hath been formerly obſerved, in the ſecond Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, the ſecond obſervation upon the Context, from the 14. to the 19. verſ. of the ninth to the <hi>Romanes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Foraſmuch as he hath choſen ſome, and but ſome to life; either he hath determined all the reſt to death, or elſe there are ſome men on whom the Lord hath paſt no certain determination,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58707:42"/>either for life or death; not for life, then he had choſen them, not for death as is here ſuppoſed. Then 1. He determines not how he wil be final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glorified by them. 2. Nor what ſhall be their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mall ſtate. 3. Nor what their way and courſe ſhall be in this life, but this is to make void a great part of his providence; then by the ſame reaſon the like may be affirmed of the Angels, and ſo the Kingdome of his providence ſtill more ſtraightned, and he in effect denyed the Univerall and ſupeam Ruler.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The deccree of Reprobation for ſome hath been already proved, and there being no reaſon any where hinted in the Scriptures, nor eaſily imaginable why ſome of the non-Elect ſhould be Reprobate, and not all; It muſt needs be granted of them all.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Foraſmuch as in Election, life and all bleſſings for life are prepared, and all depends upon Election that makes for his glory, and all men in the concluſion are ſaved or damned; hence it muſt needs be that all but the Elect are Reprobate, ſo <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.15. the condemnation of all thoſe that periſh at the day of judgement is ultimately derived from their non-Election; whence it is manifeſt that upon Election de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends eternall life originally. We may therefore ſay of all but the Elect, as it is <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.12. but we ſhall not need further to inſiſt upon this, there being very few, if any, who grant the Reprobation of ſome, but they grant it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of all but the Elect.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For the ground of this hatred, why doth God decree to permit the reſt of men beſides the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58707:43"/>Elect to ſin, with certain aime at their hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in ſin, and to harden them in ſin, with certain aime at their condemnation for ſinne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> There is no ground at all but his own will for his own glory: therefore we ſay he hath hated meerly becauſe he would: for this the Apoſtle is clear, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Expreſly removing all works of man, ſo as to aſcribe all to the purpoſe of God, v. 11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Expreſly reſolving the difference betwixt the Elect and Reprobate meerly into the will of God, verſ. 15. to 24. The fuller clearing of this Scripture, making good the matter in hand, ſee in the firſt Sermon, beginning at the 11. verſ. of this ninth to the <hi>Rom.</hi> thence to the end of the ſecond Sermon, where we ſhall finde upon the 11. verſ.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Three arguments to prove that the purpoſe of God muſt be wholly of it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtles whole diſcourſe both in rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and refuting Objections from verſ. 14. to verſ. 22. clearly proving it.</p>
            <p>Hitherto that Reprobation is Gods eternal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, that it is his decree of hatred, that it is his decree for permitting to ſin, with certain aime at hardning in ſin, for hardning in ſin with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain aime at condemnation for ſin, that the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this decree is all to a man, beſides the Elect.</p>
            <p>Now follows the end of it, his own glory,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In his ſoveraigne power over man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In his revenging juſtice upon periſhing ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the riches of his mercy upon his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and ſaved ones.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:58707:43"/>
That the glory of God is the end of all, that he is all manner of waies in all his attributes to be glorified; that whatſoever his wiſdom di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates to be for his glory muſt be brought to paſs: ſee towards the end of the ſecond Sermon, where we have ſpoken to the ſecond part of the Apoſtles anſwer, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.22.23.</p>
            <p>Now theſe attributes, the glorifying where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Lord had in his eye, eſpecially in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Reprobation: Are</p>
            <p n="1">1. His ſoveraigne power over man, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed neither as pure, nor impure, but not as yet created; his decree ordaining the reſt but the Elect, unto ſin, and deſtruction by ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.20 21. And this is more fully diſcourſed, and (I think) clearly proved in the ſecond Sermon, beginning towards the beginning of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, at the fifth obſervation there, continuing to the end of the Apoſtles plea for Gods ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power, and the opening of that plea, verſ. 20.21. It is likewiſe further cleared in this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon where this hatred of God is opened, that which we have but now been upon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His juſt wrath, or revenging juſtice upon periſhing ſinners, together with his power or might for their deſtruction, verſ. 22. where we may obſerve.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The power mentioned in this verſ, is his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, his might for execution of his judgement upon the Reprobates to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; the power mentioned verſ. 21. is his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is right or authority; this refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the Creation of Man, God hath right to Create man to what finall ſtate he pleaſeth,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58707:44"/>and accordingly to order him thereto, that to the condemnation of ſinfull man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Reprobate are veſſels of wrath fitted or prepared for deſtruction, which neither on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nor mainly relates to themſelves, as corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves, and ſo bringing damnation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves, though it be true that ſo they do, but it primarily refers to God and his aime in their Creation, as is manifeſt both by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor: The Potter prepares or fits the Veſſell of diſhonour for it's diſhonourable uſe, and by the former diſcourſe, which hath been large-ſpoken to, agreeable to the Scripture other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. he hath made the wicked man for the day of evill, in his decree of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, then he had his finall deſtruction in his eye, and therefore whatſoever ſhould make for it, ſo 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8. and <hi>Jude</hi> 4.</p>
            <p n="3">3. His mercy towards his Elect, verſ. 23. this hath been formerly ſpoken to, at the end of the third Sermon, upon that part of the deſcription of Election, to the praiſe of his glorious grace.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="sermon">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:58707:44"/>
            <head>THE FIFTH SERMON:</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 11.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But the reſt were hardned.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving laid down the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive doctrine of Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, we come now to anſwer Objections.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Expreſs texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Other arguments fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening in the Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries opinion, great abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities upon the Former Doctrine.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Texts of Scripture, they are main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe, wherein there is as much ſeemingly for them, as in all other texts of Scripture, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. where it is ſaid, Gods wills the ſalvation of all men, and that they ſhould come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. where it is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed that God is not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58707:45"/>
               <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. where the Lord affirmes with an oath, that he hath no pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turn from his way and live, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.23. the Lord hath no pleaſure at all that the wicked ſhould dye, and verſ. 32. he hath no pleaſure in the death of him that dyes: Theſe Scriptures they are wont ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently to urge an edge, the Lord ſay they here declares himſelf poſitively, he wills all to be ſaved negatively, not willing that any ſhould periſh; further, that they might be ſaved, he wills their ſaving knowledge and repentance as having no pleaſure, no none at all in the death of a ſinner, no not of him that dyes, but the contrary that he turn and live; and for this the Lord engageth his own life.</p>
            <p>For Anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt give generall anſwers to thoſe Scriptures wreſted by them joyntly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Particular anſwers to them ſeverally.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Conſider on the other hand what hath been formerly cleared by Scripture: that ſome the Lord hates in order to condemnation, this hatred, his decree for permitting ſin in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to hardning, for hardning in ſin in order to condemnation; this decree ariſing above all reſpects of ſin in man, though not without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſin in him: that as the Potter of the ſame lump, makes ſome Veſſels to honour, ſome to diſhonour; ſo the Lord out of man-kind e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually repreſented to his decree, not as yet Created, fits ſome for glory as veſſels of mercy; others for deſtruction as veſſels of wrath, that the different decrees of Election and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:58707:45"/>are the originall ground of that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference which is found in the ſpiritual and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſtate of men, (the Election hath obtain'd, the reſt were hardned) That in both theſe the will of God raigns; I wil have mercy on whom I will have mercy, and whom I will, I harden; that ſome were of old ordained, fore-written to this condemnation, <hi>Jude</hi> 4. that as God hath made all things for himſelf, ſo the wicked man for the day of evill, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. that ſome are appointed or ſet to ſtumble at Chriſt, and his word, diſobedient thereto, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8. and theſe oppoſed to the Elect or choſen people, verſ. 9.</p>
            <p>We muſt ſo interpret the Scripture as it may ſtand with it ſelf; and therefore ſo the former Texts of Scripture, as that we overthrow not theſe, and the main truths held forth in them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 2. By diſtinction of the will of God.</p>
            <p>The will of God is taken two wayes, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for his decreeing will, or will of intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſometimes for his declaring will, or will of adminiſtration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His Decreeing wil determines what ſhall, or ſhall not be, of this <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.3. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.19. whatſoever he wils by this, is certainly brought to paſs; whatſoever is not brought to paſſe, it is moſt certain he thus wil'd it not; for this will of his cannot be fruſtrate, as the Pſalmiſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes, and the Apoſtle grants; for this will, all the moſt croſſe wills of men and Devils to his commands, fulfill it.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. de Corrept. &amp; grat. c.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <q>To will and to nill is ſo in the Liberty of him that wills or nills, as that he can neither hinder the will of God,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58707:46"/>nor overcome his power:</q> S. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. His declaring will ſhews what is mans du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, what being done or undone, God approves or diſproves, it is expreſt, partly in comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, partly in affording meanes; the Lord herein dealing with men, ſpeaks after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men, what they command, or for what they afford meanes, it is commonly (though not alwaies) their intention it ſhould be done: This will is ſo often fruſtrate, as the command is broken, or the means abuſed; this will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects not alwaies the event; when God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands <hi>Abraham</hi> to offer <hi>Iſaac,</hi> here is his decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring will for it, it was <hi>Abrahams</hi> duty to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, God approved of his ready obedience, but that <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſhould be ſacrificed, he intended not, as is manifeſt by the iſſue; this is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly his will, but the ſigne of his will, as to us, which ſometimes agrees to his wil of intention, ſometimes not; in reſpect of the Event, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many times his decreeing will, that his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring will ſhould not be fulfil'd; which (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other caſes, as in that of <hi>Abraham</hi> for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering up his Son) is alwaies when ſin is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; of this will, <hi>Levit.</hi> 13.34. I would, ye would not; I would, by all my Prophets for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, now by my ſelf; I called upon you, and afforded you meanes for turning to me, ye would not, ye have reſiſted my call, and abuſed the means afforded you.</p>
            <p>Hence when God is ſaid to will the ſalvation of all, not that any ſhould periſh, not the death of him that dyes &amp;c. either the note of univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality (All, not any) is ſo to be limited, or the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:58707:46"/>Will of God, ſo to be diſtinguiſhed, or both, as nothing may be aſcribed to the will of Gods intention, but what certainly comes to paſſe in the event.</p>
            <p>This concluſion therefore we lay downe for further anſwer to thoſe Texts of Scripture joyntly, and to all of the ſame purport: God never intended the ſalvation of any, but thoſe who are and ſhall be ſaved; for then ſhould his will of intention be fruſtrate, which that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We have ſeen <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.3. <hi>Rom</hi> 9.19.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The truth of this concluſion will appear by enquiry into that will of intention, which in God they imagine for the ſalvation of all without exception, it is either a compleat and determinate act of the will of God, or a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inclination in him, not in compleat opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>If the former, then is he not unchangeable, firſt determining all men to life, then reverſing that determination; but with God there is no change nor ſhadow of turning, neither can there be, all change proceeding from imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, whether of wiſdome, or power, or happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, therefore God wills not now one thing, then another, though he executes his Will part by part, and time by time, but his Will is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes one and the ſame conſtant act from all, to all eternity.</p>
            <p>But the adverſaries here chuſe the latter ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, affirming it a naturall inclination in God, not in compleat operation, to this end diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing the Will of God into antecedent, or
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:58707:47"/>fore-going, and conſequent, or following.</p>
            <p>The antecedent they define a naturall incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in God, whereby he wills the ſalvation of all, before he conſiders a certaine act (as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> ſin) or ſome certain acts, as other ſins in man: The conſequent will whereby he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines actually the condemnation of many, this determination iſſuing from the laſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Divine Wiſdom, upon the conſideration of certaine acts in the creature fore-ſeen as thoſe which ſhall be, without his decree that they ſhall be. For anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If this diſtinction were admitted, it could not reach; for this which they call the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Will of God, hath it not taken place in the breaſt of God long ſince? Hath not God to this day conſidered of all things that can fall within conſideration concerning his creature, in order to eternall life or death? Or, by what ſlow degrees do they conceive the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God to move forward? Nay, can they forme to themſelves ſuch groſſe apprehenſions of God, as that he ſhould not have conſidered all things conſiderable before the world was? If ſo, then his conſequent will is paſt for the condemnation of many by their own grant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This diſtinction is not to be admitted, as that which transformes God into a worthleſſe Idol; Being,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Againſt the ſimplicity of his ſpirituall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whereby he is what he is purely, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly in act: And this is manifeſt from the perfection of his nature, the more all pure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations are in operation, the more perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58707:47"/>there; in Angells and men the more not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an inclination to the love and feare of God, &amp;c. but the more actuall love and feare is found in them, the more perfect is their ſtate; what light is in the Sun, it alwayes actually ſhines; But the nature of God is a nature of utmoſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, therefore no inclination in him, but what in compleat operation; hence he hath been by all Divines Orthodox in this point of the perfection of his nature accounted a pure Act.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is againſt the perfection of his Wiſdom, there is no time nor moment can be conſidered, wherein God doth not actually conſider what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever can fall within conſideration concerning the creatures acts, and all things thereupon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending, and therefore no moment can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered wherein God doth not compleatly and determinately will whatſoever he wills concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his creature.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Concluſion ſtands good from the power of God; If he wills the ſalvation of all, and hath power in his hand for it, then all ſhal be ſaved: It is a ruled Caſe, <hi>Quod volunt potentes agunt omnes,</hi> whatſoever any one really wills, if he have power in his hand he wil do it; what is further imaginable for doing a thing but wil and power? What ſaith <hi>Arminius</hi> here? he wils the ſalvation of all, but <hi>mode convenienti,</hi> after a fit manner: For anſwer briefly; The ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all either may be brought to paſſe after a fit manner, or it may not; if it may, then ſtill the argument ſtands good, he wils it, and it may be fitly done, and he hath power to doe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:58707:48"/>it, why is not then done? And indeed that it might be done after a fit manner if he pleaſed, is manifeſt, becauſe after the ſame manner he gives grace to ſome, and perſeverance in grace, he could do it to all; If it may not be done af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a fit manner, and yet according to their ſuppoſall God wills it, then he wills ſomething which cannot be done after a fit manner; how great an abſurdity is here faſtened upon the Will of God, which is the rule of all cleare, righteous, and fit proceedings? This is a will beſeeming a child rather then God; Or, what will they ſay further? Though he wills it, yet for as much as it makes more for his glory that all be not ſaved, therefore all ſhall not be ſaved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But if it makes againſt his glory that all ſhould be ſaved, then he wills it not, if God could will what makes againſt his own glory, and that way whereby he hath determined fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to be glorified, he could ſin againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; according to this ſuppoſall, there are lines running croſſe in the breaſt of God, and he is at ſtrife with himſelfe. That what the Poet ſpeakes of the weake elements amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, theſe Prophets ſpeaks of the one, perfect God.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Frigida pugnabant Calidis, humentia ſiccis,</l>
                  <l>Mollia cum duris, ſine pondere habentia pondus.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Cold things with hot, moiſt things with dry did fight,</l>
                  <l>Soft things with hard, and weighty things with light.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:58707:48"/>
This laſt expreſly, weighty things with light, his former Will, as a thing of no weight, make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the weighty aime, and way of his own glory, (which is the end, and meaſure, and rule, and poize of all) muſt give way to this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Will, as that wherein there is true weight.</p>
            <p n="4">4. From the happineſſe of God;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bradwardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.8 <hi>parte Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rollarii.</hi>
               </note> If he be perfectly happy, whatſoever he wills ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be brought to paſſe, happineſſe is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and perfect good, and it is more happy to have whatſoever is willed, then to want it; for if the wanting of one thing willed doth not in any degree diminiſh happineſſe, then neither doth the want of another thing willed, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing added to nothing makes but nothing ſtill, then neither doth the want of a third, fourth, and ſo on in the concluſion then he may be as happy who hath nothing that he wills, as he that hath all things that he wills: But this common ſenſe abhors.</p>
            <p n="5">5. From the Knowledge of God; If from all eternity he knowes who ſhal be condemned, then did he will their condemnation, and that antecedently to this knowledge, he therefore knowing it, becauſe he hath willed it; for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he knowes as that which ſhall be, he knowes either in it ſelfe, or in himſelfe; hee knowes it not in it ſelfe, whilſt as yet it is not, but nothing but himſelfe was before the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world, therefore nothing in it ſelfe could then be knowne to him.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But as we ſee what is preſent in certain moments of time, ſo he in his eternity comprehending at once and together all time, (for his eternity is the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:58707:49"/>entire poſſeſſion together and at once of a boundleſſe life) ſees before all time whatſoever is in any part of time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That in his eternity he may ſee any thing in it ſelfe, there is required not only the exiſtence of his boundleſſe life together and at once but the co-exiſtence of the thing it ſelfe to be ſeen, and therefore as man ſees not any thing in it ſelf in one moment of time, which is not in that moment, but ſhal be in an after mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo neither doth God ſee any thing in it ſelfe before all time which is not, but in time, otherwiſe he ſhould ſee time in it ſelfe before all time; which is a contradiction, and here is no ſhadow of imperfection in God, but an impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility in the thing; and what is here ſaid for the thing it ſelfe, is as cleare for all created cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the thing, they cannot in themſelves be ſeen before all time, they themſelves being but in time, what he knowes then from eternity as that which ſhall be, it is in himſelfe that he knowes it, if in himſelfe, in his will.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In God there is a threefold knowledge Firſt, an apprehenſion of the nature of things, this may be ſhadowed by thoſe formes which we finde in our owne minds, when we think of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing meerly according to the ſimple nature of it, as when a builder hath the Platforme of a houſe in his mind, but proceeds no further, either to determine it ſhall, or ſhall not, may or may not be built: thus in the Divine Nature there is the apprehenſion of all things, poſſible, impoſſible, poſſibilities, and unpoſſbilities, but that herein he doth not determinately know what ſhal be is manifeſt, becauſe thence it would
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:58707:49"/>follow, that he apprehends no more then the things that are, and ſhall be.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The knowledge of what is poſſible, what may or may not be determinately; and this he knows in his own power, whatſoever is poſſible to be done, is therefore poſſible, becauſe he hath power to bring it to paſs; but herein doth he not determinately know what ſhall be, becauſe then he ſhould be of power to do no more then he doth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It remaines then that the knowledge of what ſhall be, is founded in his will; how did he know the world ſhould be, and ſhould be this and no other, before it was? in his mind are thouſands of other formes and repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and he was able to have made it of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother form, and other kind of Creatures, ſo that here he could not know it ſhould be, and that it ſhould be this; but herein he knows both that it ſhould be, and that it ſhould be this, and no other, becauſe he wil'd that it ſhould be, and that it ſhould be this, that it is: If God knew then from all eternity, that all ſhould not be ſaved, and who they were, herein he knew it, becauſe it was his will that all ſhould not be ſaved, and that theſe ſhould be they which ſhould not be ſaved: But as hath been former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly noted, the Arminians are very creperous in point of Gods knowledge of the ſtate of man, in order to eternal life, allowing no determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and certain ground of it, either in God or Man.</p>
            <p>Thus much for anſwer in generall to theſe Scriptures joyntly, now more particularly.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:58707:50"/>
1. To thoſe two Scriptures, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. where it is ſaid God would have all men to be ſaved, and to come to the knowledge of the truth, and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. where it is ſaid, that God is not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance: theſe Scriptures free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from that generall interpretation, ſo he that wills that all ſhall be ſaved, as he wills that they ſhould come to the knowledge of the truth; ſo he is not willing that any ſhould pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, as he wils that all ſhould repent; But is it the Lords will of intention, or his decreeing will, that all without exception ſhould come to the knowledge of the truth, and to repentance? the contrary is manifeſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the denyall of meanes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From the denyall of his ſpirit to many who have the means.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the denyall of meanes. 1. He affords not to all the neceſſary means; inſtances of this are ſo evident, as cannot be gain-ſaid: for the firſt 4000 years well nigh, the world generally was over-looked, the means of knowledge, the diſcovery of the Covenant of God, onely in the Church, and that Church ſhut up firſt in the families of the Patriarchs, afterwards in the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle nation of the Jews; hence that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30. and 16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 25.26. hence the Jews ſo ſtartled when the door of faith was ſet open generally to the Gentiles; The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf, muſt by a Viſion from heaven, be taught the counſell of God, for the call of the Gentiles, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Since the comming of Chriſt, to this day, is
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:58707:50"/>the Goſpel preached in every Nation without exception? are there no Pagan Nations in the world?</p>
            <p n="2">2. He hath ſometimes denyed the means to thoſe whoſe hearts he hath ſeen leſs obſtinate in caſe the means had come to them, then others unto whom he hath ſent the means, and left them to periſh in the obſtinacy of their hearts againſt the means ſent; thus it was betwixt <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> on the one hand, and <hi>Capernaum</hi> on the other, by our Saviours own Teſtimony.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>All in</hi> Adam <hi>were taken into the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. If it was true, it reacheth not, how ſhall his poſterity in after generations, come within the call of Grace, or to the knowledge of the Goſpel, meerly upon that ground that <hi>Adam</hi> was once poſſeſt of it for them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is utterly falſe, for then ſhould <hi>Adam</hi> have been a root of Goſpell righteouſneſs to his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, whereas it is Chriſt in oppoſition to <hi>Adam,</hi> that is ſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>They had the meanes of knowledge in their Ancestours long ſince, who by their unworthy working have loſt them, for themſelves and poſterity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If that was granted, it would not thence follow that God would that their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity ſhould come to the knowledge of the truth.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This ſuppoſeth their Anceſtours a common Stock, forfeiting for their poſterity, Goſpell priviledges all the world over; but it is plain that there were ſome Nations which never had the Goſpel among them, till many years after the death of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:58707:51"/>
Object. <hi>The Creation holds forth ſo much of God, that if man would improve it ſo farre as he might by the power of nature, God would then reveale the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel to him, and give him preventing grace; and this law he made with Chriſt, for the merit of his paſſion, ſo that thus all men have the meanes of ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge initially in the Creature, and it is in their hands to improve thoſe initiall meanes to the obtaining of the ultimate meanes in the word of the Goſpell, hence they teach that the Sun, Moon, and Stars, preach the Goſpell</hi> Rom. 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This Tenent is meerly Jeſuitical, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown by the more Orthodox of the Papiſts themſelves, by theſe, or ſome of theſe following Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God in revealing the Goſpel, is found of thoſe that ſought him not, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is not in him that willeth, nor in him that runneth, but in God that ſheweth mercy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.16. whereas according to this Tenent, onely to him that by the improvement of naturall power, wills and runs, mercy ſhould be ſhown.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He will have mercy, on whom he wil have mercy, and whom he will he hardens, <hi>Rom</hi> 9.18. where the originall ground of ſalvation is aſcribed meerly to the will of God, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this Tenent, his will is ſuſpended upon mans work.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Who made thee to differ? and what haſt thou that thou haſt not received? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. the graduall difference found amongſt the Saints themſelves, is from God by what they receive; much more that ſpecificall difference betwixt Saints and Sinners.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:58707:51"/>
5. The greateſt of ſinners who have moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed their naturall Talents, as Publicans, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets; and ſuch as the Apoſtle reckons up, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9.10. are called, when many more reſtrained, and better qualified for moral vertues are paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by. Non habeo &amp;c. <hi>There is nothing that I can behold in chuſing men to ſaving grace; ſhould I in my thoughts be permitted to the tryall of this Election, but either greater wit, or ſmaller ſinnes, or both; let us add if you pleaſe, boneſt and profitable acts; whoſoever therefore he is, who is intangled and defiled with the ſmalleſt ſins, (for from all who can be free?) and of quick wit, and accompliſht with the choiſeſt acts, ſeemes a fit man to be choſen to grace; but when I ſhall thus determine, ſo will he laugh at me, who hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the weak things of the world that he may confound the ſtrong, and the fooliſh things of the world, that he may confound the wiſe, that I beholding him, and with ſhame corrected, laught at many, who both compared with ſome ſinners, are more chaſt, and with ſome fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, are Orators, &amp;c.</hi> Anguſtine. Ad Simplic. Lib. 1. ad finem fere.</p>
            <p n="6">6. According to this ſuppoſition, there is no place for preventing grace, but it is prevented debt, when a ſinner is converted, ſo that it over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws it ſelf; not grace, becauſe it is of works, and ſo not preventing, becauſe prevented by fore-going works, in the improvement of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall powers.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But it is for the merits of Chriſt, and therefore of grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> But where it is of works, it is not of grace, ſaith the Apoſtle; therefore this, hath Chriſt no more merited, it (being the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:58707:52"/>of grace) then that we ſhould be juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by works; by both which, grace would be made no grace: as for that Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.18. compared weth the 19. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> it is a moſt ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous wreſting, to apply it to this purpoſe; It is plain there, that they whoſe ſound goes forth, &amp;c. are the Apoſtles, and ſent tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers preaching the word of the Goſpel, to the eare; by whoſe preaching faith is immediately begotten, upon hearing, verſ. 14.15.16, 17 not the Sun, Moon, and ſtars, holding forth the works of God to the eye, by which men are remotely prepared for the Goſpel, and faith by it; and what is alleadged out of the 19. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> is ſpoken alluſively; the courſe of the Goſpel in the hands of the Apoſtles and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, compared to the courſe of the Sun in the ſkie: Thus much for the denyall of means.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the denyall of his ſpirit in regard of ſaving operation, to many who enjoy the means: The ſame word preached is to one the ſavour of life to life, to another the ſavour of death to death; whilſt ſome are converted, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are hardned: obſerve here,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is God that makes the difference. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. the effectual call of a ſinner in ſaving il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination, faith and repentance is the guift, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.17. and 2.8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.29. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26.27.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is of meer grace, without reſpect of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer works, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.5.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Lord herein uſeth an abſolute liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.8.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:58707:52"/>
4. He gives in the call of a converted ſinner, both the power, and the acting of that power; to ſuch as are not converted he gives neither: the former part of this is clear by the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Texts, proving it to be his gift; both the former and the latter is clear, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.44.45. no man can come without the fathers drawing and teaching; therefore where this is not, there is not ſo much as the power, but where this is; not onely can they, but they do come; hence the converſion of a ſinner is an effectuall and a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar work of God; and if God did the ſame for thoſe who are not converted, which he doth for thoſe that are, they ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted too; but this we have ſeen before.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Lord in this proceeds according to his decree, for converting ſome, by hardning o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers againſt the means, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18. for conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.4.5. for hardning, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.37. to the 42. that the Jews were not converted by the powerfull miniſtry of Chriſt, was hence, ſaith the Evangeliſt; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord had long before determined their hardning, and foretold it; <hi>Eſay</hi> in his time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the glory of Chriſt, as he was to be revealed by his coming in the fleſh, and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (adding miracles to his Sermons) to the Jews; propheſied of theſe Jews, that they by his word and works ſhould be hardned: Hence then it will be manifeſt upon the ſumming up of theſe particulars, that by all here, cannot be meant every one without exception; not ſo much as the declaring will of God, in afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the meanes being for all in that ſenſe;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:58707:53"/>much leſſe his decreeing will, according to which he diſpenſeth himſelfe thus differently, both in affording and applying the meanes; we will here conclude with
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. de Geneſ. ad literam. c.</hi> 10.</note> S. <hi>Austin, God could</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>turn the will of the wicked into good, he could 'tis plain, becauſe he is omnipotent, why there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth he not? becauſe he will not; why he will not, it is with himſelfe,</hi> (penes ipſum eſt) <hi>for we ought not to be wiſe above what behoves.</hi> Here the wiſdom and Soveraignty of God betake themſelves to their height, he that will here ſtraine his eye, ſhall loſe his ſight; he that will needs be ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theſe depths, ſhall loſe his plumb; he that will ſearch out the majeſty, ſhall be over-whel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the glory. Thus much for the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Anſwers to thoſe two Scriptures joyntly, now in the laſt place to each apart.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. It is manifeſt by the Context, it is meant of all rankes and orders of men, whether Kings, and thoſe in Authority, or Subjects, and thoſe under Authority, (as in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. no difference of Nation, ſex, condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, exclude from Chriſt) and there was ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all reaſon from the ſtate of thoſe times for the Apoſtle to ſpeake to this; The Kings and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the world being then great perſecutors of the truth, and profeſſed enemies to it, it might ſeem labour in vaine to pray for ſuch a deplored kind of men; therefore the Apoſtle uſeth this reaſon, that of that order of men as well as others, God hath his Elect whom hee will ſave.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. To us-ward ſaith the Apoſtle, who are theſe? The Apoſtle an
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:58707:53"/>Elect and Believing perſon writing to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed Jews, who for the Goſpell ſuffered perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, themſelves Elect Believers and ſanctified, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1, 2. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1. The ſum then is this, God delayes the day of his great judgement, that he might firſt gather in all his Elect ones, not willing that any of them ſhould periſh, and as this is applied to them of that genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amongſt the Jewes, ſo it looks further to that harveſt of Gods Elect amongſt them, which in their great call, yet to come, is to be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.28. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For the other two Scriptures, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. and 18.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Lord wills not their death by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring will, for as much as he hath commanded them to return, and given them means for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For his decreeing Will, the Lord by it wills not their death, according to the purport of their charge againſt him, to which here he anſwers.</p>
            <p>They charge the Lord, firſt, as unjuſt, puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the children for the Fathers offences, the children themſelves free, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.2. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as unmerciful, as though inexorable againſt repentant ſinners; this the Lord ſhewes to bee charged againſt him in his anſwer to them, chap. 18. mentiening ſo often that the wicked returning ſhall find mercy, and both theſe we find charged upon him, chap. 33. unmerciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, v. 10. injuſtice, v. 17. had this charge been true, the Lord had delighted in the death and torments of periſhing ſinners, as a Tyrant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in the blood of his Subjects, had not
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:58707:54"/>willed their death as a righteous judge wills the death of a Malefactor. The Anſwer then is, That God doth not ſo will the death of a ſinner, as that he is liable to the Charge of Injuſtice, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning without fault, or to the charge of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifulneſſe, inexorable againſt repenting ſinners, but for their juſt and true incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hath he ſo fully expreſſed himſelfe, not to will the death of a ſinner, no not of him that dies, in the meane time upon immovable grounds formerly laid downe, the Lord wills the death of thoſe that die, for the glory of his own power and juſtice, ſeen in their condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>[The like Anſwers in generall are to be given to thoſe Seriptures ſo frequently alledged, and as often perverted, for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall Redemption; which Scriptures the adverſaries are wont to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject againſt the Doctrine of Predeſtination. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and particular anſwers, <hi>1.</hi> The main Texts alledged by them, do of themſelves, together with the Context afford: <hi>2.</hi> The Analogie of Faith in many fundamentall Doctrines clearly taught in the word of truth, amongſt which this of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination hath the leading place; in which whoſoever is truly inſtructed, is ſurely anchor'd againſt that windy error.]</p>
            <p>Hitherto we have anſwered theſe two laſt Scriptures, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. and 33. upon ſuppoſition that eternall death was there ſpoken of, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is indeed temporall judgements which they there complaine of, and about which the Lord cleares himſelfe, as is manifeſt, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.2. with <hi>Jer.</hi> 27. to the 31. verſ. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. from the 24.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58707:54"/>to the 30, verſ. where it is evident, the deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Land was the matter of their quarrel and complaint, they were ſo far from complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that God had given them over to hardneſs of heart, ordering them thereby to eternall death, as that they juſtifie themſelves as ſuffering undeſervedly; That was indeed the complaint of an humble and repenting people, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63.17. but theſe were quite of another ſtraine. To this the ſum of the Lords anſwer is; That they are the Authors of their own wo, he is ſo far from taking pleaſure in their undeſerved ſufferings, that would they be righteous they ſhould be free from miſerie, to this end hath he commanded them to turne from their iniquities, and affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them means for the ſame, that obeying they might live. A great ſtir the Arminian Nation is wont to make with theſe Texts of Scripture, diſputing all the while upon a falſe interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and meerly perverting the queſtion here held forth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="sermon">
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:58707:55"/>
            <head>THE SIXTH SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 11.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Election hath obtained it, and the reſt were hardned.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E come now to other their maine Objections, which tend upon ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſall of the former Doctrine, either to accuſe God, or excuſe Man</p>
            <p>Object. 1. <hi>Say they, according to this Doctrine of Reprobation, God muſt be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of ſin, and ſo be guilty of ſin, and this they urge upon three grounds eſpecially:</hi> 1. <hi>In that he decrees it, thence there is a neceſſity of mans ſinning.</hi> 2. <hi>In that he acts in it, producing as the firſt cauſe thoſe acts in and by man, to which ſinne cleaves inſeparably.</hi> 3. <hi>That unto</hi> Adam <hi>he denied that grace, without which it could not be, that as to the event be ſhould perſevere in working righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What is here alledged as the grounds of this Objection, is owned by this Doctrine, but
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:58707:55"/>the charge of the Objection is denied, as having here no footing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the decree;—1. That God decrees that ſin ſhould be, hath formerly been proved, but that hence he cannot be concluded the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of ſin is evident, becauſe the decree, as ſuch, is an act immanent in himſelfe, not immanent upon the creature, it being the property of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent acts to put nothing in the object.— 2. There is upon the decree of God a neceſſity of mans ſin, as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 6 <hi>de Geneſ. ad literam. c.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith well, <hi>The Will of God is the neceſſity of things:</hi> But, 1. It is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity not abſolute, but upon ſuppoſall, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall, not of compulſion, but of conſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for as much as God hath ſo decreed, it cannot otherwiſe come to paſſe but man ſhall ſin, yet doth he ſin freely, chuſing ſo to do, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting neither by conſtraint, nor from a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of naturall neceſſity; but of this we ſhall ſpeake more in anſwer to the third Objection, which chargeth this neceſſity as inconſiſtent with the eſſentiall liberty of mans will. 2. There is a neceſſity of the ſame kind for mans ſinning, if we grant that God fore-knowes his ſinne, if God fore-knowes that man ſhall ſinne, then muſt it needs ſo come to paſſe, otherwiſe God fore-knowes that ſhall be, which ſhall not be, but this clearly involves a contradiction: We muſt then either grant a conditionall neceſſity of mans ſinning, or deny Gods preſcience. 3. Upon ſuppoſall that man ſhall ſin without the decree of God, God himſelfe ſtands under the like neceſſity, a neceſſity upon ſuppoſall, or of conſecution, for as much as man ſhall ſinne,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:58707:56"/>and is ſo fore-knowne of God, or whether ſo fore-knowne or not, there is now no liberty left to God for preventing mans ſinne, ſo that whileſt we feare to leſſen mans liberty, by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing him to ſtand under a conditionall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity ariſing from God, we feare not to leſſen Gods liberty ſubjecting him to the like neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ariſing from man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For Gods acting in the ſins of men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. That the great Creator as the firſt cauſe produceth all motion in all creatures, ſeems not obſcurely to be taught by the Apoſtle, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28. as he is ſet forth the Author of life, in him we live, of being, in him we have our being; ſo of motion, in him we move, and as the Apoſtle quotes there <hi>Aratus</hi> one of the Heathen Poets, ſo ſutably another of the Poets ſings, <hi>Eſt Deus in nobis, agitante caleſcimus illo;</hi> God is in us, he moving we wax warm.</p>
            <p>To me it ſeems one of the foure letters of his Name <hi>Jehovah,</hi> to be the Author of all being, and therefore of all operations, in all creatures their operations, not being nothing, and to aſcribe to any creature onely upheld, not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by God, to produce its own motion ſeems to transfer Divinity to the creature, and dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from it in God. I ſhould thinke the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the creature, in dependance upon the Creators moving, to be like that Engine, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.—16. a wheel in the middeſt of a wheel, the motion of God incompaſsing the creatures mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and moving it within it ſelfe: And I would further make this Quaere, Doth God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold all and every being? I do not know that
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:58707:56"/>this is by any denied, divine conſervation and ſuſtentation of whatſoever is; but if motion be upheld by him, it is produced by him; for it being a ſucceſsive entity or being, how is it otherwiſe upheld then by Production? and if life be upheld, motion is; this terme, life, inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this terme, motion, life being in the living creature, the ſupreme and univerſall principle and power of operation actually in operation. But to inſiſt no longer upon this; we affirme clearely, as that which comes cloſer to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent queſtion and concludes it, whatſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of this diſcourſe, for all creatures in all their motions depending upon God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That God as the ſupreme and univerſall Governor acts the wills of men, turning them which way he pleaſeth in their motions, is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſed in Scripture, and there is not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle depending upon this truth both for our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and comfort.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For Scripture-teſtimony, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.1. What are the preparations of the heart there, but the thoughts, deſires, and inward workings of it? Theſe are from the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.1. What is there ſaid of the Kings heart is as clearely to be affirmed of the hearts of other men: What more expreſſe? <hi>It is in the Lords hand, like the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of water, he turneth it which way ſoever he will;</hi> Is any thing more eaſily turned this way or that way, then a water-courſe? So eaſily doth the Lord turne the hearts of men, how are they turned but by their owne motions? They ſo move then by their own principles, as the Lord is the firſt and ſupreme mover, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.46. He
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:58707:57"/>turned the Enemies hearts to pitty his people, and he gave them favour in the ſight of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> Exod. 11.3. So he likewiſe had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore turned their hearts to hate his people, and to deale ſubtilly with his ſervants, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.25. further teſtimonies (though theſe might well ſuffice) will come in as we ſhall ſhew the duties hereon depending, which we now come to in ſome few inſtances.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hereupon therefore it is our duty.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſeek after the Lord that we may know him, and give up our ſelves to him; it is further manifeſt by theſe teſtimonies, how we are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that of the Apoſtle, <hi>In him we move,</hi> the Apoſtle thence requires this as the duty of all men living, having theſe experimental wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes within them of their great Creator, in their life, being, motion, they are not, they ſtir not without him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To glorifie God with all humble adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the great Lord in whoſe hands is our breath, and whoſe are all our wayes, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.23. all our wayes, even to the preparations of the heart, and all the motions and iſſues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as we have ſeen.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To take heed with ſear and trembling to the motions of Gods ſpirit in us, in the things that concern ſalvation, that we neglect them not <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12.13. for as much as we cannot act but as acted by God, and he acts us by our own wills; firſt principled by his grace, then moved by his grace, then moved by his ſpirit; take heed we be not wanting to ſecond theſe motions of his in us.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:58707:57"/>
4. To pray unto God that he would incline our hearts to himſelf, and to his waies, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.35.36. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.18.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To praiſe God for whatſoever good incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and operations we have found in our hearts, 1 <hi>Chron</hi> 29.14. for two things doth <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> there bleſs God. 1. That they had what to offer. 2. They had hearts wherewith to offer; the willingneſſe of their hearts was from the Lord, as well as all that ſtore they had to offer, and this he further acknowledgeth in prayer, verſ. 18.19.</p>
            <p>Other duties we might inſtance in, as humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; as in the laſt example, verſ. 14. <hi>What am I, and what is my people?</hi> In giving the moſt to God, they received the moſt, in that they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved hearts to give, &amp;c. But I forbear inſtances, onely one ſpeciall caſe making for our no little comfort, in times of greateſt temptation, by the prevailing of wicked men againſt us.</p>
            <p>The Lord hath as well their hearts as hands in his power, to make them pitty us, favour us, as we have ſeen; he hath made promiſes to this purpoſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.4. So when any mans wayes pleaſe the Lord, he will make even his enemies to be at peace with him; and it muſt not now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the hand of man, whether the Lord ſhall be true in his promiſes or no, which it muſt do, if he doe not act and turn the hearts of men as he pleaſeth; <hi>Jacob</hi> truſted to this when he made that prayer, <hi>Gen.</hi> 43.14. ſuppoſing <hi>Joſeph</hi> to be ſome godleſs-Egyptian. Now let any man judge whether theſe teſtimonies, and duties thereupon depending, import no more but this;
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:58707:58"/>that God conſerves man, and upholds his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, propounds objects, and perſwades, then ſtands a looker on, leaves it meerly in mans power to act, or not to act; this way, or that way; ſo as for the event, it may or may not not be, this or that, nothing certain or deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd.</p>
            <p>Hence then we affirm, that God as the great Creator and univerſall Ruler, produceth all operations, and motions in the heart of man, even thoſe to which in man ſinne cleaveth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably
<note n="*" place="margin">Much more to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſee lib. 5. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra. Julia. c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>God workes in the heats of men to incline their wills whitherſoever he will; whether to that which is good for his own mercy, or to that which is evill for their merits,</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> But now to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Objection, <hi>How then is he himſelfe free from ſin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. God works as the ſupream mover, man as the proper ſubject; that is, in whom is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the ſinfull action: this is one ſtep clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God in the caſe in hand, to make it plain by inſtances; The Sun ſhining upon a Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, raiſeth a ſtink; the Sun ſtinks not, but the dung-hill in which is the principle of the ſtink, and it is by the operation of the Sun that it ſtinks: ſinfull man is as the dung-hill, God as the Sun. A Clock falſe made, moved by the poiſe ſtriks falſe; the poiſe moves true, though the clock ſtrike falſe. By the ſhining of the Sun upon a falſe Dyall, the hours of the day are falſly given, the Sun is true in his courſe, yet without his motion the Dyall would not lye. A skilfull writer uſing a pen with an hair in it, for fair letters, blots are made; yet he writes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:58707:58"/>to as exact art with that, as with the cleaneſt pen, the fault is only in the pen. A skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Muſician playes upon an Inſtrument out of tune, the muſick jarres, the inſtument ſounds a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe; yet he ſhews no leſſe skill, neither tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth the lawes of Muſick any more, then if he plai'd upon a well tun'd inſtrument. Sinfull man is the falſe Clock, the falſe Dyall, the blotting Pen, the jarring inſtrument; God in his motion is the Poyſe, the Sun, the Writer, the Muſician; from God is the motion, in man is the principle of the evill in the action.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God works as the Author of nature, man as a morall Agent: that is, as ſtanding under a law, which whilſt he obſerves, or violates, his action is free from fin, or ſinfull, ſin being the tranſgreſſion of the Saw of God: now thoſe actions are the ſame conſidered as naturall, which as morall differ extreamly, and God works uniformely in thoſe actions which are naturally the ſame, though morally very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and in point of good and evill, contrary. Inſtance, <hi>Adam</hi> eating the forbidden fruit, doth the ſame thing in naturall conſideration, which he had done in eating the ſame, had it not been forbidden him; yet then had his eating been a lawfull and blameleſſe action, whereas now it was moſt ſinfull: nor onely the outward action of eating, but his will and deſire of eating (ſuppoſing him to have will'd, and deſired it not forbidden) hath been the ſame in nature that it was when he deſired it forbidden; yet in one caſe free from ſin, in the other deeply guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Whence riſeth this difference; not from the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:58707:59"/>different exertion of natural power, or a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in the operation of his will as naturall, but from his different condition; becauſe he is in one caſe under a law forbidding, from which in the other he was free: Now God here works as the Author of nature, and uniformely; the difference of mans condition varies not his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration: as the Sun ſhines uniformely upon a Dung-hill, and upon a Garden, though the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect be contrary; the weights move uniforme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the true, and the falſe clock, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Another inſtance; ſuppoſe one man in heat of affection ſlay his adverſary juſtly, another unjuſtly his friend; here is innatural conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, one and the ſame action in both, the ſame exertion of naturall ſtrength outwardly in the motion of the Arme, the ſame animoſity inwardly ſtirred up in the motion of the will; therefore the operation of God, who works as the Author of nature one and the ſame for kind in both; the difference in morall conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration is found onely in the men, the one acting according to the law of God, the other contrary to it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God works according to a pure rule, man contrary to a pure rule, Gods rule is the dictate of his own wiſdom, for his own glory; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the wiſdom of God repreſents as making for his glory, that God wills and acts accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly: now it is plain by the iſſue, and by Scripture teſtimony, that the wiſdom of God hath ſuggeſted the way for his finall glory, in mans finall ſtate, ſuch as ſuppoſeth the ſinne of man, making way for that glory; God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:58707:59"/>according to this rule, both determines that man ſhall ſin, and acts ſinfull man in thoſe actions of his, to which as in, and from man, ſin cleaves unavoidably. Mans rule is the Law of God, man in ſinning, though he fulfils Gods intention (for who hath reſiſted his will? the Jews in crucifying Chriſt, did whatſoever the hand and counſell of God had before deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to be done) which is not his rule; yet he acts againſt his law, which is his rule; and therefore God acting according to his pure rule is blameleſſe, man working contrary to his pure rule, guilty.</p>
            <p>The third ground whereupon they will have the Doctrine of Predeſtination formerly aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to charge God as the Author of ſin, is, <hi>That unto</hi> Adam <hi>wa denyed that grace, without which it could not be, as to the event, that he ſhould actually per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in his righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To affirm that God is the Author of ſin, is granted on both hands blaſphemy, and therefore whatſoever the Scripture teacheth concerning Gods diſpenſations to man about the firſt ſin, or fall of <hi>Adam:</hi> this concluſion cannot thence be infer'd that God is the Author of ſin. Now all the queſtion is, what the Scripture here tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth: This ſay we, <hi>That unto</hi> Adam <hi>was denyed that grace, without which it could not be, as to the event, that he ſhould ſtand,</hi> and this we clear by theſe following ſteps.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Adam</hi> was created in the Image of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. that is [whatſoever more is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended] <hi>in righteouſneſs and true holineſs</hi> Ephe. 4.24. herein was that ſtate of habituall righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:58707:60"/>whereby he was able to do whatſoever good he ſhould will to do: all the faculties of his ſoul were fitted to work according to the rule of righteouſneſs without any interruption; it was not then with him, as it is now with the regenerate, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. with whom to will is preſent, but how to perform that which is good they find not; he had withall by that habituall righteouſneſſe a power to will that which was good, even all that good which God according to his law engraven on his heart might require at his hands, free from any principle byaſſing him to evill: and this power, and this righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, had all his poſterity in him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he was denyed the grace whereby he ſhould actually ſtand, is manifeſt by the event; fallen he is, but God was able to have afforded him that effectuall grace, whereby his fall had been prevented, as he hath dealt with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, who keep, and for ever ſhall keep their firſt ſtanding; and had that grace been afforded him, he had ſtood, for it is a contradiction to ſay he had that grace, whereby he ſhould not onely be able to ſtand, but ſhould actually ſtand; and yet grant that he ſtood not, he had then both a power to wil all that was good and to do all that good which he ſhould will; but to will, and to do that for which he had a power, was not given unto him. A ſound eye hath the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of ſeeing, there is the power; but that it may actually ſee the object before it, it muſt have light: An Inſtrument truly made and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, hath in it the power and principle of ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding harmoniouſly; but that it may yield it's
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:58707:60"/>harmony, the skilfull touch of the Muſicians hand is neceſſary: Hence St. <hi>Auſtin,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib. de cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reptione &amp; grat. c.</hi> 11.</note> The firſt man had not that grace by which he never could be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill; but that grace he had in which if he would abide, he never ſhould be evill. Such an aid of grace he had, as which he might forſake if he would, and in which he might abide if he would: not ſuch as whereby it might come to paſſe, that he ſhould will to abide. Then comparing it with that aid which beleevers receive in Chriſt; ſo much greater is that aid which is given by Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, unto whom it ſeemes good to God to give it, that not onely we have that, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which we cannot perſevere, although we ſhould will; but ſo great, and ſuch that we ſhall will: for there is in us by this grace of God, both in the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and holding with perſeverance that which is good, not onely to be able to do that which we will, but alſo to will that for which we are able.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Cap. 12.</note> Again, <hi>To the firſt man, who in that goodneſſe wherein he had been made upright, had received to be able not to ſinne, to be able not to dye, to be able not to forſake that goodneſſe; was given an aid of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, not by which it might come to paſſe that he ſhould perſevere, but without which he could not be able by his free will to perſevere: but now to the Saints predeſtinated unto the Kingdome of God, by the grace of God not onely ſuch an aid of perſeverance is given; but ſuch an one, as that to them perſeverance it ſelfe is given; not onely ſo, as that without that gift they cannot perſevere; but ſo, as that by this gift they may not but perſevere.</hi> Much more to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe frequently in him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It could not be that he ſhould have that grace, whereby as to the event he might ſtand,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:58707:61"/>as to his own fitneſſe he had by his habituall righteouſneſſe a power of ſtanding, he was ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitually fitted for it; but that it might ſtand, as to the event, there muſt be further a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous influx from God, of light upon his mind, of holineſſe upon his will actuating his habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all power; Now that this ſhould be afforded him, it could not be, that being ſuppoſed for which the Scripture is clear.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God knew certainly that he ſhould fall; that man is put to a very hard ſhift, who ſhall deny Gods certaine knowledge from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of <hi>Adams</hi> fall, or of any event whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; and the free confeſsion hereof would be refutation enough to moſt mens appreheſions (the impreſſion of Gods perfection, as for other Attributes, ſo for knowledge, deing deeper ſet upon the heart of man, then by a little miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sophiſtry to be wiped out) of that unluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky opinion, which can be no otherwiſe ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted then by deſpoiling God of his eſſentiall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties. Now if God knew certainly that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> ſhould fall, then it cannot be that he ſhould have that aid of grace whereby he might as to the event ſtand; for then God ſhould know certainly that that ſhould be, which yet certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly might not be, namely, <hi>Adams</hi> fall, whereas for as much as God knowes certainly that it ſhall be, it may not for the event, but be.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That God hath decreed his fall; If God had decreed that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould fall by his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, (and in that decree of his own permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion it was that he knew certainly that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould fall) then could it not be that <hi>Adam</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:58707:61"/>ſhould have that grace whereby as to the event he might ſtand; for then Gods Adminiſtrations to man might make void his owne decree, but that God had ſo decreed we have formerly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: Let us gather up a brief diſcourſe about it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God decreed the making and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the workes of his hands for his owne glory, as the end of all, is moſt unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he decreed particularly that glory which comes to paſſe from his creature; either that particularly, or another particularly, or laſtly, none particularly, but his glory general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and indefinitely; not another particularly, it is too abſurd to ſay that he decreed what comes not to paſs, and decreed not what comes to paſs, ſuch an apprehenſion doth at once ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly overthrow his wiſdome and power; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did he decree his glory only generally and indefinitely, that apprehenſion neceſſarily ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth a defect in his wiſdome for dictating di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly and particularly the way of his glory, and aſcribes unto God the weakneſs of man diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing from generals to particulars, which is alwayes accompanied with, and ſuppoſeth imperfect knowledge and power.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That he decreed his owne glory compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſively, to wit, all that glory in every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular which ariſeth to him from the creature, this is cleare (to wave other Arguments) from the two former particulars, becauſe his glory is the end of all his workes, as his glory parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly as it comes to paſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That glory of his in the final ſtate of man being ſuch as ſuppoſeth ſinne, (for how ſhall
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:58707:62"/>ſome be ſaved in mercy, others in juſtice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned without ſin?) and particularly <hi>Adams</hi> fall, and in him all his poſterity, it muſt needs be that God decreed that glory of his, and that way of his glory.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But why doth God give a righteous law in charge to</hi> Adam, <hi>inables him with habitual righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs for the fulfilling of that law, and yet deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines that he ſhould not fulfil it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We have from cleare and unſhaken principles but now proved that God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed that way of his glory, or the glory of thoſe Attributes in mans final ſtate which neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily ſuppoſeth ſin, not to the decree, but to his glory; but if God had not made man righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and given him a righteous law in charge, and left him to the violation of that law, there could have been no ſin in man; herein is ſinne, man tranſgreſſeth that law which he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to obſerve, and for fulfilling whereof he had a power, <hi>Adam</hi> in himſelfe, and we in him</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>By what right doth God condemne may for ſinning, when he hath firſt decreed, and then his diſpenſation towards man is according, that he ſhall not have that grace without which it cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe come to paſſe but he ſhall ſin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But by what right doth duſt and aſhes lift up its head againſt the great Creator in theſe bold enquiries?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whatſoever appears by the Word of God to be his Will, there is no place for this enquiry; By what right? The VVill of God being the rule of righteouſneſs; <hi>Nay,
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Gen. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra. Manich c.</hi> 3.</note> ſo the higheſt rule of righteouſneſs, that whatſoever he wills, in as much as
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:58707:62"/>he wils it, it is to be accounted righteous: whereever therefore this queſtion is asked,</hi> Why hath the Lord done thus? <hi>the anſwer muſt be, becauſe he would: but if thou ſhalt goe on in asking,</hi> but why would he? <hi>Thou now ſeekeſt ſomething greater and higher then the wil of God, which cannot be found</hi> Auguſtin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Lord here ſtands upon his dominion over man as his Creator, and thereupon checks the inſolency of this enquiry: Nay but O man who art thou that replieſt againſt God? <hi>Shall the thing formed, ſay to him that formed it, why haſt thou made me thus?</hi> or hath not the Potter power over his Clay? &amp;c. It is too high a pitch for man to ſoar, to call his Creator to the Bar, and there implead him face to face.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Lords proceeding here by vertue of his Dominion, is a depth that muſt with trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling be admired, cannot be ſounded. O the depth! <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33. Wilt thou acknowledge no more in the moſt myſterious wayes of God, then what thy reaſon can graſpe?</p>
            <p n="1">1. See the refutation of thy pride in the moſt common things of natures courſe every day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thine eyes, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 38 give a clear anſwer to, and make a clear demonſtration of thoſe Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merrical, Phyſicall, and optick Problems there; here let me make the challenge to thee, which ſometimes learned
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Corolari parte</hi> 32. <hi>vertus prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipium.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bradwardine,</hi> that great Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerter of the cauſe of God, againſt thy fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Pelagius</hi> made to the prond Philoſoper de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riding Chriſtians, becauſe they beleeved what the Scripture affirmed, though they could not make it good by reaſon: <hi>Tell me thou Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>what it is that thou knoweſt thoroughly? not theleaſt mote in the Sun beames,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:58707:63"/>nor the leaſt grain of duſt of the earth, nor the leaſt drop of water; in the leaſt materiall quantity, infinite lines, figures, ſuperficiall, corporcall, divers in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, quality and kinde are contained; and therefore anſwerably infinite concluſions Geometricall, orderly ſucceeding, ſo as that the latter cannot be known but by the former; infinite Arithmeticall concluſions, in orderly dependance likewiſe: of theſe, many concluſions in themſelves demonſtrable, how many knoweſt thou? Nay, let all the Philoſophers be joyn'd together, how many of theſe infinite concluſions know they? a very few; there remaines therefore very many, not one whereof for their difficulty, and your meanneſs doth any of you, or all of you together know: A little after, the leaſt ſpark of fire, doth it not by enlightning and warming make infinite or numberleſs circles of light, and ſpheres containing and contained, as likewiſe croſſing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; numberleſſe lightſome Pyramids likewiſe, and Pyramids viſuall, and thoſe very different one from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; numberleſs likewiſe lightſome and viſuall beames incident, reflex, refract, in which are contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned infinite cencluſions, Geometrical, Arithmeticall, and perſpective; and who can fully know all theſe? In the ſame place he argues, how much leſſe can thy finite little ſoule comprehend the great God, who is every way infinite? Nay, bluſh thou Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, and be aſhamed to own ſo ſmall a God, as that thou ſo ſmall, by thy minde ſo ſmall, ſhouldeſt ſearch him out quite through, ſhould'st ranſack all his ſecrets, ſhould have a comprehenſive knowledge of him.</hi> Thus he.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe thou art a chriſtian, let us go one ſtep higher. Canſt thou comprehend by reaſon all the myſteries of faith? what? that of the three perſons in the one God-head? the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:58707:63"/>of the Son? the proceſſion of the ſpirit? what of thy ſaviours Incarnation? the diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the two natures united into one perſon? As for thoſe, who, becauſe they cannot by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon comprehend, do therefore deny theſe main Articles of our Faith; my charity is not eaſie enough to call them Chriſtians. I will conclude with St. Auſtine, <hi>Thou a man requireſt of me an anſwer; why, but I am a man too,
<note place="margin">De verbis Apoſtol. Serm. 20.</note> let us therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> beare him who ſaith, Nay but O man who art thou? thou askeſt a reaſon, a will tremble at the depth: thou argueſt, I will wonder: diſpute thou, i'le be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve; I ſee the depth, the bottom I cannot reach: S.</hi> Paul <hi>reſted, becauſe he found where to ſhut up with wondring; be calls them the unſearchable judgements of God, and doſt thou come to ſearch them? He calls them thoſe wayes of his which cannot be traced, and wilt thou needs trace them?</hi> How much better, and more Chriſtian was it, to captive our reaſon to faith, beleeving what the Scripture ſaith, even then when our reaſonleſſe reaſon replies, <hi>How ſhould theſe things be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Is not this great Cruelty in God to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point his Creature by his decree to deſtruction? and here they are wont to raiſe a mighty out-cry, and by odious compariſons to aggravate this Charge; Tygers (ſay they) and Bears, and all the moſt ſavage Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, are kinder to their young then ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To clear the queſtion. 1. God appoints not the innocent, but the guilty creature to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; though the fore-ſight of ſin be not before his decree for ſin, and deſtruction: yet his decree appoints that ſin ſhall be before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and deſtruction ſhall be for, and by ſinne.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:58707:64"/>
2. To refute the Objection.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Muſt they not acknowledge that by Gods permiſſion man ſins? that by Gods appointment the ſin of one man hath caſt the whole world in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſtate of condemnation? that in the iſſue, the greateſt part of man-kind is deſtroy'd? that ſometime the whole world was given up to raigning ſin, and periſhed generally in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> eight perſons excepted? that for many ages the Lord ſuffered all Nations to walk in the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of their owne hearts, without God, without hope in the world? that to this day he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> many Nations to periſh without he knowledge of Chriſt, there being no other name amongſt men whereby ſalvation is had? that many to whom the Goſpel is ſent, are hardned by it? when as yet it was in the power of the Almighty to have prevented all this, and that without any the leaſt trouble to himſelf. Now if Gods do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over his Creature, doth not abſolve him of tryal at the Bar of natures Law in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (as this objection would bear in hand) how will they avoid this charge of cruelty againſt him granting what they muſt grant? would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not be cruelty in the Creature, and againſt the law of nature, to ſee their young ones torn in peices before their eies, in caſe they could prevent it; eſpecially without any hazard or trouble?</p>
            <p>After the ſame manner they argue, in charging God as the Author of ſin; it is ſin in man to wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that another ſhould ſin; therefore to ſuppoſe of God, that he wils that man ſhall ſin makes his the Author of ſin; ſo they conclude, if this be juſt arguing, there is no ſinne in the world, but God muſt be the Author of it, whether he will
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:58707:64"/>it or not (if we can imagine that God permits ſin beſides his will) for it is ſin in man to permit ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſin, when he hath power in his hand, (and that without the leaſt trouble to himſelf) to prevent it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is there the ſame kindred and Conſanguinity betwixt God, and all the ſons and daughters of men without exception, that there is betwixt the living Creatures, and their young ones? it is true we are his off-ſpring, or of his kind, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.29. inaſmuch as we have our life and being in him, and were created in his image; but to be his ſons and daughters, depends upon his Covenant in the hand of Chriſt, made on the behalf of the pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar and choſen ſeed; now for them let the whole world periſh, not one of them ſhall miſcarry, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.35. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.52. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Their own objection falls in full weight upon their own heads, who teach that ruinous Doctrine of final apoſtacy; that they who are truly the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, having embraced his Covenant by true faith, may yet fall from the ſtate of life totally and finally, and ſo periſh for ever.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Wherein doth this cruelty appear? that God ſhould condemne hardned ſinners, is that cruelty? no; that he ſhould harden wilful ſinners, <hi>viz.</hi> give them up to hardnes of heart as a puniſhment of their former ſins, is that cruelty? no; that he ſhould not recover from ſin; all the Sons and Daughters of <hi>Adam</hi> without exception, is that cruelty? no; that he ſuffered <hi>Adam</hi> to ſin, and imputed his ſin to his poſterity, is that cruelty? no; All theſe things they grant, Scripture-evidence being ſo clear for them; though ſome of them, true ſons of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Pelagius,</hi> would gladly, if for ſhame they durſt;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:58707:65"/>and ſome have put ſhame here) deny the imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, and ſo originall ſin; in one of theſe two then, or in both together, muſt be the cruelty, that unto <hi>Adam</hi> was denyed that aid of grace, without which it could not be, as to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent that he ſhould ſtand; that God decreed ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedently to the fore-ſight of ſin, the ſins of men; but it hath been proved already that this is no cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty in God, but the charge of cruelty hereupon is blaſphemy in man. Inſtance; But at the leaſt God is not ſo mercifull, according to this Doctrine, as the Scripture ſets him forth. Reply 1. And how is he ſo powerfull, and ſo perfect as the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture repreſents him, if any thing fall out beſide his decree and the full purpoſe of his will? 2. The Scriptures which ſpeak moſt this way have been cleared already, and therein we have diſcovered how inconſiſtent it is with the nature and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, that in any thing his will ſhould be fruſtrate. 3. There are two ſorts of mercies, 1. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, in the bleſſings of this life; theſe are to all the children of men, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.16.17. 2 Peculiar in the bleſſings of eternall life, thoſe which ſhall ſurely make for it; here the Apoſtle avoucheth a difference, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18. and this founded meerly in the will of God, verſ. 11.13. theſe are onely to the Elect, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.3.4 and how clear the current of Scripture is for this, hath formerly been abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly made good the greatneſs of the Lords mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is declared extenſively in the former, that they are to all, even to thoſe who live and dye his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, intenſively in the latter. 1. That they are ſo excellent in their nature. 2. That they are ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar; as we have formerly ſeen at the end of the third Sermon. So that if the Holy Ghoſt knowes
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:58707:65"/>by what argument to commend the mercies of God to man; he that denies the former mercies to belong to all, or affirmes the latter to belong to all, derogates from the mercies of God indeed.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the two main Objections made againſt the former Doctrin, accuſing God: a third now followes tending to excuſe man.</p>
            <p>Object. 3. <hi>The former Doctrine takes away the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of mans will, and ſo quits him of all ſin; liberty of wil being neceſſary to every ſinfull action.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon two grounds do they conceive the liberty of mans will overthrown. 1. In that God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed his ſin. 2. In that God moves his will, when he wills ſinfully, the motion that is from God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wil of man, determining it in its operation: whence man muſt ſin of neceſſity, and therefore not freely, and ſo his ſin is no ſin; the objection againſt the liberty of mans will is the ſame, in actions not ſinfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. For the decree.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is moſt clear by Scripture, and hath been formerly proved, that the actions of mans will both good and evill, are decreed by the Lord. Let us here onely give ſome ſpeciall and remarkable inſtances. 1. For good actions, embracing the call of God in the converſion of a ſinner is decreed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28 30. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. the faith and obedience of converted ſinners, in an holy courſe is decreed, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.4. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. The obedience of Chriſt fulfilling the will of God in performing the great work of mans Redemption, was decreed, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.7. for evill actions: The cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Chriſt by the Jews and Romans was decreed <hi>Acts.</hi> 4.27. <hi>Abſoloms</hi> inceſt was decreed, as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:58707:66"/>in that it was fore-told by God, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.11. and generally whatſoever was fore-told, as that which ſhould certainly come to paſs, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally (as <hi>Nineve</hi> his deſtruction) muſt needs be decreed, for if God have not determined, that either by his works or permiſſion, whatſoever he hath fore-told ſhall come to paſſe, then may his word be falſified: hence then the bitter perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Church by her wickedeſt adverſaries, the faith and patience of the Martyrs, in all ages is decreed. To inſtance in the rage of myſtical <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon;</hi> the faithfulneſſe of the Virgin-company, the true Church of Chriſt, overcoming her tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations: to inſtance further, in the Kings of the Earth, firſt ſubjecting themſelves unto that whore, afterwards hating and deſtroying her, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the Jewes, and with them the fulneſſe of the Gentiles; theſe are all foretold as thoſe things which ſhould certainly be, and therefore were they all decreed; and how much of the will of man, and the workings thereof, is in all theſe things who can but ſee?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Yet hence is no infringement of the liberty of mans will, becauſe the decree as ſuch, is an action in the breaſt of God, makes no change in man, or in his condition, till it come to excution.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The decree eſtabliſheth mans liberty, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as God hath decreed that man ſhall wil, it is now beyond all peradventures that he ſhall wil, for the counſels of God ſhall ſtand; but how certain ſoever it is that he ſhall wil, ſo certain it is that he ſhall worke freely; for to will, is in the motion of the will to work freely; to will, and not to act with liberty of will, is a contradiction: not only all things and operations, but their different kinds
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:58707:66"/>and manner alſo fall under the decree of God; who as he hath fitted neceſſary cauſes to work ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily: as the fire burns neceſſarily, ſo hath he likewiſe fitted voluntary, and contigent cauſes to work voluntarily (that is freely) and contingently.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But what God hath decreed uniſt neceſſarily come to paſſe, other wiſe his decree might be fruſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It muſt neceſſarily come to paſs, that is, it muſt of neceſſity come to paſs, yet not neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that is by neceſſary operation, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, if it depend upon a free and contingent cauſe, it muſt of neceſſity come to paſs, freely and contingently, here is onely a neceſſity of the event, not of the manner of production, and therefore a neceſſity of conſequence, not of the cauſe, a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity neither naturall nor violent, and the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of conſequence we have formerly ſeen muſt be granted, or we muſt both deny Gods fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, and make him ſtand under that kind of neceſſity, which we think it an unworthy thing that man ſhould ſtand under.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But may one and the ſame effect, both neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily and contingently come to paſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It may, the neceſſity being rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, <hi>viz.</hi> not ſimple, or abſolute, but reſpective or conditionall: Inſtance, 1. In the actions of God, he creates the world freely, it was in his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty whether he would create a world or no, whether this world or no; yet upon ſuppoſition that he hath decreed it, it is now neceſſary that it be in time created, neither can it otherwiſe come to paſſe but this world muſt be created. 2. In the actions of man; when Chriſt was crucified, his legs were not broken, that the Scripture might be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled which had formerly affirmed, <hi>that not a bone of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:58707:67"/>him ſhould be broken,</hi> God having ſo determined as by his Word was declared, it could not be that they ſhould be broken, yet did the ſoldiers forbear to break them voluntarily and contingently, they were neither naturally nor violently neceſſitated to forbear. Another inſtance, whether in the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God or the creature, what is done, muſt of neceſſity be done, it is impoſſible that a thing ſhould be done, and not done at once; yet if there be any free or contingent act in the world, which is granted on all hands, liberty and contingency muſt be granted to ſtand with that neceſſity. This Objection is yet further cleared by theſe two fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Rules.</p>
            <p n="1">1. All effects produced by the creature are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary or contingent, according as the creature it ſelf, the next cauſe is in its manner of operation: Natural agents are neceſſary cauſes, as fire, the Sun, they worke neceſſarily, the fire in burning, the Sun in ſhining, producing alwayes the ſame action for kind, heating, inlightning, working to the utmoſt of their power, therefore their effects are neceſſary. Voluntary agents are free and contingent cauſes, they work freely and contingently, they ſo act one way, as that they have an intrinſical power to act another way, ſo wil, as that they have a power to nil, ſo nil, as that they have a power to wil the ſame thing as they ſhal like or diſlike; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their effects are free and contingent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In regard of God, the firſt cauſe, all effects in the world are both neceſſary, and contingent, or free; in regard of his intrinſicall liberty, whereby he may chuſe whether he wil produce them or not they are free, or contingent; ſo for the ſhining of the Sun, and the burning of the fire, though they
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:58707:67"/>be neceſſary effects in regard of the Sun and fire, their next cauſes, yet are they contingent in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of God, in whoſe liberty it is to afford or with-hold his influx for their production: So the Creation of the world, all effects depending im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately upon the Wil of God, Angels, or Men, are in regard of their immediate cauſes free and contingent; all the moſt caſuallevents, as the lot in the lap, in the ſame regard contingent; yet all theſe upon ſuppoſition of Gods decree, are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary. Thus much for the decree, and the neceſſity thence ariſing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the wil of man is moved by God, and by that motion of his determined in its operation, doth not take away the liberty of mans will.</p>
            <p>For clearing this, we muſt take notice of a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold liberty; there is the liberty of
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Independence</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Choice.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The liberty of Independence, where the will ſo acts, as it is not acted by any higher cauſe; this is peculiar to the will of God, he onely is inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, upon any other in the motion of his wil; the wills of all men and Angels are ſo under his dominion, as that they are moved by him; this hath formerly been proved, as to men, that God as the great Creator and univerſall Ruler, moves the wills of men which way ſoever he pleaſeth: many more arguments might be brought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate that the liberty of mans will muſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the effectuall motion of God upon it; ſo act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it as acted, may act, eſpecially is this cleared in the Doctrine of Converſion and Perſeverance; but to inſiſt upon theſe would be an unſeaſonable digreſſion, eſpecially the thing in hand having been already proved.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:58707:68"/>
2. The liberty of choice; where the wil in its operation doth what it likes in the light, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſentence of the practical underſtanding, there are two acts of the will, to will and to nill, to chuſe, to refuſe: Now herein is the liberty of the will expreſt: 1. That in theſe operations it doth what it likes, it wills with liking, it nills with liking; yea with liking doth it nill even the object which it diſlikes, and therefore it ſo wills or nills the preſent object, as that it hath power at the preſent to will what it nills, or to nill what it wills; was there an impreſſion of liking upon it contrary to what is, yet though it have this oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite power at the ſame time, it hath not a power to produce oppoſite acts at the ſame time, it being impoſſible that a prevailing liking, and diſliking of the ſame thing ſhould ſtand together at once. 2. That it act in the light and upon the ſentence of the practicall underſtanding, that is, the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding as it ſhewes and determines wherein is our happineſſe or good for the preſent moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable, and what makes neceſſarily or mainly for it; this muſt needs be required to the liberty of the will, becauſe the will is a rationall appetite, and therefore cannot otherwiſe will or nill, then as the underſtanding repreſents the object good or evill; and therefore whatſoever it wills it wills as good, cannot will any thing as evill, for then it ſhould act not as a rational appetite that is, not as the wil; it is true, that the underſtanding miſtakes many times good for evill, and evill for good, whence good is either true or apparent, but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it is that the will chooſeth, it is that which the underſtanding repreſents as good, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though the will have a power when it wills
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:58707:68"/>the preſent object to nill it, if it ſhould like ſo to do, yet ſo long as the underſtanding repreſents it good to will it, and evill to nill it, it cannot like to nill it.</p>
            <p>Hence it is manifeſt, how man in the operation of his wil, differs from neceſſary Agents, whether na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Agents, as the fire, or ſenſitive as the bruit beaſt; they are determined by the force and inſtinct of nature: naturall Agents without either appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion or choice, or any ſhadow of either; ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Agents have onely the light of ſenſe according to which they like or diſlike, and therefore not ſo much a true choice as a ſhadow of it; man in the operation of his wil, doth what he likes or diſlikes in the light of the underſtanding. Now to apply this to anſwer the objection, the liberty of Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence being peculiar to God, where this liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of choice is, there is all that liberty of will which is found in the Creature, Angell, or man.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But how doth determination to one part ſtand with this liberty of choice?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> There is a double determination 1. To one of the contrary objects, good or evill, morally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood; that this may ſtand with the liberty of the will is clear: On the one hand, God himſelfe, Chriſt, the Angels, the glorified Saints, can will onely that which is good; neither have they po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to will what is evill; yet in them is the higheſt liberty of will, without which there is no holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. On the other hand, the Devill, the damned, the hardned, we may add all the unregenerate, can onely will that which is evill yet in all theſe the will is free, (naturally free, though morally enſlaved) without which there was no ſin; deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination then to one of theſe contrary objects,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:58707:69"/>takes not away the liberty of the will. 2. There is a determination to one of the contrary acts, to will or to nill; neither doth this take away the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the will, for then the exerciſe of its li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty ſhould take away its liberty, when ever it either wills or nills, it is for the preſent not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different about the object, but determined; now as the Adverſaries ſuppoſe the will to determine it ſelf unto, and in its owne operation, thereby not deſtroying, but exerciſing its liberty, ſo wee affirme that God by his motion determines it, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it by its owne principle, and according to its owne nature, that is, by the underſtanding de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining it to its operation, and ſo moving it, as in the vertue, and by the efficacy of his motion it doth whatſoever it likes in the light of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, with a power to the contrary if it ſhould like; ſo that whatſoever is required to its liberty, ſtands faire with the motion of God deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining it; and the more firmely it is in its opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fixed to the object, the more fully doth it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe its liberty, as liking more vehemently what it doth, but ſtill in the light of the underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the main Objections, where the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to theſe ſhall ſatisfie; what Objections re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, will prove but waſh way, where ſatisfaction is not received about theſe, it will be but loſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to proceed to others.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <opener>
               <date>
                  <hi>June</hi> 5. 1648.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Downame.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:58707:69"/>
            <head>ERRATA,</head>
            <p>Page 1. line 18. for onely of life, read onely way of life, p. 4. l. 7. for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> degree r. decree, p. 5. l. 30. for into this maze, r. in this maze, p. 7. l. 12. for the Scripture, r. that Scripture, p. 12. l. 30. for Law, r. love, p. 15. l. 26. for fore-light, r. fore-ſight, l. 33. for in the firſt ground, r. is the firſt ground, p. 19. l. 13. for it peradventures, r. it, at perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures, p. 31. l. 23. for harden to Reprobate, r. harden the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, l. 32. for it uſe, r. its riſe, p. 32. l. 24. for 1. r. 2. p. 50. l. 29. for apart together, r. apart, and altogether, p. 52. l. 10. for line of whom, r. line excepted of whom, p. 56. l. 2. and 3. for glorfying, r. glorying, p. 57. l. 21. for whereby Chriſt, r. whereof Chriſt, p. 59. l. 17 for two John, r. 6. John, p. 65. l. 9.10. for to the praiſe, r. 10. To the praiſe, p. 70. l. 24. for underſtand, r. underſtood, l. 33. for when, r. whom, p. 75. l. 20. for, makes for his glory, r. makes for glory, p. 80. l. 8. for urge an edge, r urge and edge, p. 89. l. 3. for 1. r. 2. p. 90. l. 8. for he that wills, r. he wills, p. 93. l. 10. and 13. for acts r. arts, p. 94. l. 27, for is the gift, r. is his gift, p. 95. l. 17. for by hardning others, r. by; hardning others. p. 106. l. 12. for heat, r. heart, p. 107. l. 17. for Saw r. Law.</p>
            <p>Some other ſmall ſlips there are, and divers miſ-pointings which I omit.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
